<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A description of new Jerushalem being the substaunce of two sermons deliuered at Paules Crosse. Containing, a briefe discouery and conuiction of certayne doctrines held of Romanists and Brownists against the Catholike and Apostolike faith. / By Henoch Clapham..</title>
            <author>Clapham, Henoch.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 125 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B07515</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC"> 76698313</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5336.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S91453</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">76698313</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 76698313</idno>
            <idno type="VID">184222</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B07515)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184222)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 2241:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A description of new Jerushalem being the substaunce of two sermons deliuered at Paules Crosse. Containing, a briefe discouery and conuiction of certayne doctrines held of Romanists and Brownists against the Catholike and Apostolike faith. / By Henoch Clapham..</title>
                  <author>Clapham, Henoch.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 113, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Valentine Simmes.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601..</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's device (McK. 332) on t.p; initials; head- and tail-pieces.</note>
                  <note>Errata: verso of p. 113.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-G⁸ H⁷.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in: Peterborough Cathedral.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Ezekiel XLVIII, 35 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Second Advent --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Brownists --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:184222:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184222:1"/>
            <p>A deſcription of new <hi>Jeruſhalem</hi> Being The ſubſtaunce of two Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons deliuered at Paules <hi>Croſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Containing, A briefe Diſcouery and Conuiction of certayne Doctrines held of Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts and Browniſts againſt the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike and Apoſtolike faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By Henoch Clapham.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.10.</bibl>
               <p>None of the wicked ſhall haue vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but the wiſe ſhall vnderſtand.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed at London by Valentine Simmes. 1601.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:184222:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:184222:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable <hi>Sir William Ryder knight,</hi> Lord Major of the Ho. Citie of London.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing (Right Honorable) to ſend this litle <hi>Deſcription of New Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſhalem</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to print, (tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh far from being done in print) I pondred to whom I might with expediencie dedicate the ſame. At last, I ſet downe my reſt on <hi>Him,</hi> who was in the publique place where I preached, then preeminent: Who alſo heard both the Sermons, and therewithall did both times with Ho. curteſie receaue the Preacher home to Table. All this to your Ho. ſelfe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184222:3"/>
            <p>And in verie troth, I know not well to whom rather it appertaineth: ſeeing, beſides the former respects, the Lord hath made you (next vnder her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie) chiefe Ouerſeer in our Ho. Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, for cheriſhing vertuous acts, and for pruning and cutting off all tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions from the ſame.</p>
            <p>Tranſgreſſion is two fold: either th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> whereby <hi>Religion</hi> is abuſed, or that which tranſcendeth <hi>Humain equitie.</hi> God and Man are made one in Chriſt, nor ſhould Religion and Righteouſnes be ſundred, though distinguiſhed. The firſt is by God his Miniſters to be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: The ſecond by Maieſtrates to be proclaimed: and the breach of both, by their Sword to be puniſhed.</p>
            <p>What need of a ſharpe ſword and of a two edged word there is, let the rank growth and impudent cariage of <hi>Impietie</hi> and <hi>Iniquitie</hi> teſtifie that. Eaſie ſalues are for eaſie ſores, but Fistulaes muſt be bitten, &amp; Gangrenes be pared off. I need not ſignifie to your
<pb facs="tcp:184222:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> Lo. ſomuch what vnrighteouſnes ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowes (euery Court and Seſſion rings that <hi>Alarum</hi>) as what falſe coine in Religion daylie is diſperſed by Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nists, Brownists, Anabaptists, Arrians, Familiſts, and ſuch like factions. Theſe that counterfait the Q. coine, are pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed accordingly: But for adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating, clipping, and flat changing of Chriſtes coine (the precious <hi>written-word,</hi> ſtamped with Gods image) how litle this is looked vnto, &amp; how ſeldom, and then alſo how ſlenderly corrected, it is able to make the heart of Gods ſubiect to bleed.</p>
            <p>As the ſword and word are for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing ſubiection vnto Maieſtrates: ſo much more be they ordained for cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing obedience vnto God, Duetie to earthly powers, it ſhould lead vs (as by the hand) to that duetie which we owe vnto the Prince of Princes. Elſe, while we liue to Man, whoſe breath is in his noſthrils, we dye to God, whoſe breath doth kindle the fire of <hi>Tophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184222:4"/>
            <p>In lighting <hi>Ieruſhalems</hi> torch, I therwith diſcloſe falſe lights &amp; ſleights wherby <hi>Babels</hi> marchants would vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their painted wares. Looke how I drew it at firſt for helping mine owne memorie, ſo I ſent it to the examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſo it was returned authorized to the preſſe. And that falleth out to be the ſame that was preached for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, howſoeuer ſome other Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents drew in ſome other particular diſcourſes, not ſo neceſſarie the preſſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides the two Sermons, I haue ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyned a <hi>Brief</hi> of that I purpoſed then alſo to haue deliuered. All I preſent, and yet all that nothing to the ſacred Texts deſert. As I could, I haue done, and ſo in all holie dutie I remaine,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Ho. obliged,</hi> Henoch Clapham.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:184222:4"/>
            <head>To al that wiſh Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalems proſperitie, the grace of God be <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloued, if euer, now faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and prayer is highly neceſſary: as for the whole catholike Church, ſo (of our partes) more ſpecially for our owne particular Church, a member of the vniuerſall. As I am not a little acquainted with forraine Churches their corruptions (but the leſſe contagious, becauſe they be in further part of the catholik body remoued from vs) ſo, not to diſſemble our own (alas, alas) hovv is our Sauiors ſpeech fulfilled vpon vs? Faith (faithfully profeſſed) hard to bee found, when vnder color of Reformation, people feare not to complot Deformation: euerie fantaſticke ſpirite attempting what is good in his owne eyes and priuate iudgement, as though there were no King in Iſrael, no God in heauen. For Charitie, the moſt of vs haue exiled her. Faith iuſtifieth alone, ſay we: tis true: but adde with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>That faith which worketh by Loue:</hi> euen by Loue termed the <hi>Bond of Perfection,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:184222:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>Fulfilling of the Law:</hi> for neuer ſhall that Tree bee approoued which bringeth not foorth good fruit. Trees are not planted for liuing to themſelues, but for benefiting others alſo. The diuel once ſought to leade vs ſo to gaze on the merit of workes, as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all we ſhould examine howe wee ſtood in the faith: now he labors to cauſe vs ſo to admire Faith, as wee ſhould forget (I had almoſt ſaid, forſweare) good works. Thus Satan is euer in extremities: but the people of God muſt know, that as GOD hath bleſſedly ioyned true faith and good workes togither: ſo, none can but by the inſtinct of Satan attempt to put them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunder. If we ſo beleeue, and ſo walke, then God ſhall not be weary of doing vs good, nor we haue occaſion to feare the threates of Belial.</p>
            <p>As all euilles are contagion, ſo falſhood in doctrine is Leauen for infecting many: and a Canker for corroding like a viper. For, from whence proceede euill workes, but from euill Beliefe, falſe perſwaſion of God and his proceedings? The late Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſtes will that their Pope may erre in <hi>Fact,</hi> but not in <hi>Faith.</hi> A blinde aſſertion: for no erroneous fact, but it proceeds from erroneous Faith. As for example: <hi>Peter</hi> denieth his maiſter, a foule Fact. From
<pb facs="tcp:184222:5"/> whence proceeded this, but from a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, that it ſhould be good for him <hi>then</hi> to do <hi>ſo?</hi> The like may be ſaid of any fact. So that we may conclude rather, A man may erre in faith, yet not in fact (for hee may ſtay to act his error) but neuer erre in fact, but firſt the diuell hath ſowen errour in his faith. And heereof it commeth that Romaniſts on the one hand; &amp; Browniſts, Anabaptiſts, Arrians, &amp;c. on the other hand, they beſiege our Church with ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall artillery: euery Sect thinking they therein doe God very good ſeruice, and their Fact paſſing commendable: whereas (alas) ſuch proceeding is but the fruite (to thinke the beſt) of errour in Faith, corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in iudgement.</p>
            <p>It is then a duty of Gods Miniſters, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially owing to the people, namely, to hold out the word of trueth for enlightning the ſenſes. And becauſe <hi>Illumination</hi> without <hi>Sanctification</hi> doth make a man but a <hi>Bala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am,</hi> an Iſcariot, a diuell: herewith they are to pray much, that GOD would ſanctifie ſuch light and knowledge to true obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</p>
            <p>Amongeſt the reſidue of Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, I (the leaſt of many) do labour in this worke daily. Though I haue no particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
<pb facs="tcp:184222:6"/> flocke to attend on by peculiar calling: yet am I called to the worke of Chriſt, for miniſtration of worde and Sacrament to God his ſheepe, in this catholike ſheepfold. A calling had at home, and not vnſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed vnto by forraine Churches. Before thine eyes I haue heere lighted a candle, deſcribing new Ieruſhalem, the praiſe of the whole earth. This is not done ſo parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly as might be wiſhed, but as the time could affoorde. <hi>Moſes</hi> (from mount <hi>Neboes</hi> toppe termed <hi>Piſgah</hi>) he ſeeth <hi>Canaan</hi> and <hi>Iſraels</hi> diſtinct lotts: but <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> (the diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of theſe manſions) hee ſawe it more thorowly. If that I haue done may occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion any other to do better, my lot is good. Meane time accept of this <hi>Deſcription of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſhalem,</hi> as of a light, directing to a <hi>Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Babel:</hi> that (if God thinke good) I may heereafter publiſh. Which if, ſome things heere omitted, may there be fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſerued.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Southwark</hi> by <hi>London,</hi> 
                  <date>1601</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:184222:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A DESCRIPTION</hi> of new Jeruſhalem</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EZEK. laſt chap. laſt verſe, and laſt clauſe.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the Name of that Citie from a Day <hi>(ſhalbe)</hi> Iehouah-ſhammah.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O the end this vpſhot of <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Prophecye may be the cleerer too our ſenſes, Let vs ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marily conſider the whole bodie of this Prieſt-like Prophecie, In this viſionarie volume we may obſerue two ſorts of Viſions: the firſt, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, the ſecond, ſpeciall. That is
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:184222:7"/> generall, it is that one ſtately ſight which the Prophet hath in the firſt chap. containing a treaſurie of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the whole Catholike bodie of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> ſeeing therin the Church may behold, how <hi>Iehouah Aelohim</hi> the great God, is mounted vpon the ſtately Chariot of the world, hauing the raynes in his hand, gouerning by the mightie outgoings and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of his eternall ſpirit: wherby he alſo ſeeth cleerely into all things. Come heauen and earth together, run all vpon wheeles, not Fortune, but the mightie <hi>Iehouah,</hi> he turneth all the frame of Nature vnto his owne moſt worthie glorie, and the common vtilitie of his beleeuing Iſrael.</p>
            <p>In the other viſions we more ſpecially obſerue, firſt, the Prophets calling: ſecondly, a particular diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of the Iewiſh typicall matters. In his calling (contained in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond and third chap:) we cleerely
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:184222:7"/> may ſee, how togither with his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination vnto this ſtately kind of miniſterie the prouident God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth vnto him a Rowle of wiſdome to eate: Becauſe hee ſendeth no prophet in mercy to his church, whome firſt he enricheth not with the hid treaſure of his burning ſpirit, for conſuming vp the ſpirituall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, that ſtand as hinderances in the way of his kingdoms paſſage.</p>
            <p>In theſe viſions that concerne the bodie of the Iews more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, we may conſider: firſt <hi>Iehouah</hi> caſting them out for their ſinnes, ſpecially for filling the Temple with pictured Beaſts (beaſtlie affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in them, who ſhould haue bin themſelues a Temple for the holy ghoſt) auerting and turning their backs vpon the Lord: for the which <hi>Iehouah</hi> leaues the Temple, drawing his glorie to the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, forſaking them and their City; that ſo the <hi>Chaldeans</hi> with vnbridled
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:184222:8"/> crueltie might ouerturne all, deſtroy a multitude, and carry a remnant into captiuity. This their eiection laid downe in ſundry viſions, in the ſecond place is vttered, God his free acception of this caſt-away people. And this is don, firſt by deſtroying his peoples aduerſaries: ſecondly by powring a bounteous bleſſing vpon this people: firſt by revni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> (the two and ten tribes) into one, for the glorious ouerthrow of <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog:</hi> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly by meaſuring vnto his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <hi>Canaan</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> for new. That I ſay, for new, it is becauſe all in this reſtauration is new. For in reſpect of the letter fully, when were the ten Trybes (who ſchiſmed in <hi>Rehoboams</hi> time, and in <hi>Hoſheahs</hi> time were tranſported by Aſſur,) when were they revnited to <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Beniamin?</hi> When did theſe 12. Trybes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> make ſuch hauock of Gog and Magogs huge armie?
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:184222:8"/> When was Canaan ſo remeaſured, and theſe new lots (diuers vnto <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuahs</hi>) when were the Trybes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted in them? Other things tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Citie and Temple might come into a <hi>Quaere:</hi> but that is ſaid vnto the learned is ſufficient, for manifeſting that the fulneſſe and ſpirit of this prophecie was to be expected of a new <hi>Iſrael,</hi> comming out of a new Babylon, vnto a new Canaan, endowed with a new Citie and Temple. Inſomuch as this New-church might well ſay with the Apoſtle,<note n="“" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.17.</note> 
               <hi>Old thinges are paſſed away, behold all thinges are become new.</hi> As <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſaw them in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, ſo muſt we conſider them in the ſpirit. For (as a certaine Auncient well ſaith of <hi>Moſes</hi> fed in the mount &amp;c.<note n="*" place="margin">Macari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. 12.</note> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>What ſoeuer was done,</hi> (or, fell out) <hi>it was a figure:</hi> and (as th'apoſtle ſpeaketh,<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 10.1.</note> 
               <hi>a ſhadow of good thinges to come.</hi> Now to the Text.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:184222:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>And the Name of that Citie, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Citie ſpeaketh he of? The whole hyſtorie before conſidered, we eaſily vnderſtand of what Citie he treats according to the letter and open narration, (namely of <hi>Ieruſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> in <hi>Paleſtina</hi>) which according to this Prophecie was to be turned into a new Citie: and therewith to be inueſted with a new name. Firſt to this old Citie, the ſhadow; then afterwards to the new Citie, the ſoule and ſubſtance of the former ſhadow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ieruſhalem</hi> in <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> 18. chap. and laſt verſe, is termed <hi>Iebuſi,</hi> (of the vncircumciſed <hi>Iebuſits</hi> that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habited the ſame) and is there ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the lot of <hi>Beniamin:</hi> ſpecially the ſuperiour part, <hi>Zion</hi> (2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 5.) together with the ſacred Temple ſeated vpon the Mountaines, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by <hi>Moſes,</hi> the ſhoulders of <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iamin.</hi> But elſe, from <hi>Ioſhuahs</hi> 15. chap. and laſt verſe, it ſhould alſo
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:184222:9"/> fall within the lot of <hi>Regall Iudah.</hi> This do ſome reconcile thus: it was <hi>Beniamins</hi>
               <note place="margin">Per ſortem.</note> by lot, but <hi>Iudahs</hi> by <hi>Beniamins</hi>
               <note place="margin">Per conceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionem.</note> conceſſion or graunt: or elſe, it was by reaſon that God (for after purpoſe) had interming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Beniamin</hi> with <hi>Iudah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the Name <hi>(Ieruſhalem)</hi> diuers are diuerſly minded. Some haue taken it to ariſe from the greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſignifying<note place="margin">or Sacrificer.</note> a <hi>Prieſt</hi>) and the auncient hebrew terme <hi>Sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> in Engliſh, <hi>Peace, Heb.</hi> 7.2. as if it were termed, <hi>Sacrifice</hi> or <hi>Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers-peace,</hi> or <hi>Peaceable-ſacrifice.</hi> But ſuch compoſition ſhould haue been to the <hi>Iewes,</hi> but as a Lynſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woolſy garment, or the matching of an Ox and an Aſſe together, or the ſowing of their ground with Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellaine, inhibited by the law. For what had <hi>Hebers</hi> people to do with <hi>Iauans</hi> tongue? Or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did the ſpirit of prophecy abhor <hi>Hebers</hi> language &amp; the Dialects following out of it,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:184222:10"/> that ſo he ſhould to the old Synago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue adde the Grecians language? The continuall practiſe of the old teſtament doth euer witnes the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie.</p>
            <p>Others more rightly deduce the former part of the word alſo from the Hebrew, and hereof be two iudgments. Some take it to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded of <hi>Iireh (Gen.</hi> 22.14.) a terme which Abraham put vpon the mount<note place="margin">1. Chro. 3.1.</note> 
               <hi>Moriah,</hi> whereon the Temple was built: and of <hi>Shalem</hi> the auncient name of this citie (<hi>Gen.</hi> 14.) what time (<hi>Melchi-zedek</hi> did inhabite there. Which two termes (<hi>Iireh</hi> and <hi>Shalem</hi>) contracted into one, do make <hi>Ieruſhalem.</hi> And ſo in this one word; the Iewes are put in mind of God his prouident ſight in Abrahams offring vp his <hi>Iſaac:</hi> and of <hi>Melchi-zedeks</hi> bleſſing pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon Abraham, after his returne from ſlaughter of the Kings.</p>
            <p>Others compound it of <hi>Iebus</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:184222:10"/> 
               <hi>Shalem.</hi> And very certaine it is, that this Citie at ſeuerall times enioyed theſe ſeuerall names. But theſe two termes drawen into one, ſhould ſo yeeld, not <hi>Ieruſhalem,</hi> but <hi>Iebuſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem.</hi> Anſwere is made, that <hi>B.</hi> is tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into <hi>R.</hi> for myſterie ſake, (as <hi>Saul</hi> was turned into <hi>Paul, Sarai</hi> into <hi>Sarah, Abram</hi> into <hi>Abraham,</hi>) the change of letter being a ſacramental ſigne of the Cities change from ſin to Sanctitie: no longer to remaine a cage of ſuch vnclean and hatefull byrds, as were the Iebuſhits: but a Citie for the Saints, an habitation for the mighty God of Iaakob. And this myſticall ſenſe, the <hi>B.</hi> turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>R.</hi> will further imply, if ſo they be conſidered in <hi>Hebers</hi> language: where <hi>B.</hi> is termed <hi>Beth,</hi> (in Engliſh an <hi>Houſe) R.</hi> is termed <hi>Reſh,</hi> (in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh an <hi>Head</hi>) as if one would ſay, that vnclean <hi>Houſe</hi> became the <hi>Head</hi> or Metropolitane citie. And in verie truth, euery one of vs in our
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:184222:11"/> firſt creation was <hi>Shalem,</hi> at peace with God: but by Apoſtacie and miſcreation, we became in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond place <hi>Iebus,</hi> a receptacle of vnclean ſpirits: but by recreation, and the new gift of God, we are made <hi>Ieruſhalem,</hi> a Citie for the great king.</p>
            <p>The truth reſting betweene theſe two laſt repeated iudgements, you may demaund, whether of them vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters the truth? I anſwer, both ſpeak probably, for any thing yet vnto me reuealed. If of <hi>Iireh</hi> and <hi>Shalem,</hi> it ſignifieth <hi>viſion of peace:</hi> if of <hi>Iebus</hi> and <hi>Shalem (B.</hi> turned to <hi>R.</hi>) it alſo commeth to be (as before) <hi>Iireh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalem,</hi> by contraction, <hi>Ieruſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem:</hi> the <hi>viſion of peace,</hi> or the place of ſuch viſion as bringeth <hi>True peace.</hi> For all falſe viſion doth ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect but a falſe peace; compared by <hi>Ezech.</hi> chap. 13.11. &amp;c. to vntem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered morter, that will not hold out a ſtorme, when the wrath of God
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:184222:11"/> commeth out againſt ſinners. Whereas that <hi>viſion</hi> which iſſueth from God and his Miniſtrie, it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freth (and to the Beleeuer giueth) a <hi>Peace,</hi> which the Receiuer ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer need to repent of. This tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Iudaicall and typicall <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſhalem</hi> premiſed: Let vs now exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the remoouall of this ſhadow for eſtabliſhing the ſubſtance.</p>
            <q>And the Name of that Citie from a Day <hi>(ſhalbe)</hi> Iehouah-ſhámmah.</q>
            <p>As if he ſhould ſay, From the day of this new Cities building, a terme ſhall be put vpon this Citie, which ſhall be vnto it as a ſacrament of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houahs</hi> preſence there for euer. So that, herein we are to obſerue, Firſt, the remooual of an old Citie, 2. for building of a new: with the remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uall of an old name, for baptizing this Citie into a new.</p>
            <p>Firſt, touching the remoouall of the old, <hi>Haggai</hi> (including Citty,<note place="margin">Hag. 2.7.</note> Temple, Land,) doth tearme the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:184222:12"/> pollicie eccleſtiaſticall and ciuill, an heauens and an earth which God would ſhake after a while, euen then ſhake the ſame, what time the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of the Nations (that is <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi>) ſhould come. And becauſe we ſhould not doubt what he meaneth by ſhaking, marke how the Author to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> deſcants thereon: <hi>Yet once more will I ſhake,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.27.28.</note> 
               <hi>not the earth onely, but alſo the heauens.</hi> And this (word) <hi>Yet once more,</hi> ſignifieth a remoouing of thoſe things which are made, that the things which are not ſhaken may remaine. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeeing we receiue a kingdome which cannot be ſhaken, &amp;c.</hi> In all which is plainly concluded, that the old pollicie of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> togither with their whole kingdome, it was to be ſhaken, and by the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> remooued: that ſo we might receiue the new kingdome of <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> that neuer was to be ſhaken or remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. The Prophets are plentifull
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:184222:12"/> in this poynt, and the Author to the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> maketh this doctrine as the mayne argument and ſubiect of his Epiſtle. And what doth <hi>Iaakob</hi> in his prophecie vpon <hi>Iudahs</hi> tribe inferre principally, if not this, that <hi>Iudahs</hi> tribe ſhould continue till <hi>Shiloh</hi> come,<note place="margin">Gen. 49.10.</note> but <hi>Shiloh</hi> once come he ſhould gather the people to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: and ſo conſequently diſſolue <hi>Iudahs</hi> tribe and annihil their City and pollicy? <hi>The tribe ſhall not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part Iudah</hi> (that is, Iudahs tribe ſhall not be diſſolued and confounded) <hi>till Shiloh come, and the people ſhall be gathered vnto him.</hi> And how appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant this is, let <hi>Iudahs</hi> preſent diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the loſſe of their <hi>Canaan,</hi> the ſubuerſion of their city, the ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of their prieſthood and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice (and that for theſe 1500. yeeres, and vpward) let that their tragike experience be as ten thouſand ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions to this doctrine.</p>
            <p>Nor were theſe heauenly Moſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:184222:13"/> heauens and earth ſhaken and remoued for a ſeaſon, but for euer. For from the day of that ſhaking, we receiued a kingdome that was neuer to be remooued. Now, if with our vnmooueable kingdome (the kingdome of Chriſt) we ſhould after a ſeaſon expect the Iewiſh kingdomes reſtauration vnto their Moſaicall pollicie, this were to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> ſhadowe and ſubſtance. I do not define whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther euer the <hi>Iewes</hi> ſhall be gathered into ſome forme of gouernment, but I conclude that their figuring kingdome was (as a ſhadowe) euer to be aboliſhed, that ſo the figured and ſubſtantiall kingdome of <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah</hi> might be planted for euer.</p>
            <p>The Synagogues kingdome was notably ſhaken, when (Meſſiah hanging vppon the croſſe) the earth quaked, the vayle rent, the ſtones cloue a ſunder. Yea, they might take knowledge of a new world, when
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:184222:13"/> as the graues (togither with the Lord of reſurrection) did ſend out their dead,<note place="margin">Matth. 27.51 &amp;c.</note> who walked into the City and ſhewed themſelues to many: put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in mind of <hi>Daniels</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12.2.</note> reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of many. About 40. yeares after, their Temple was fired, their city by the Romanes raſed to the ground, and their whole common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth vaniſhed as a ſcrowle folded togither.<note place="margin">Euſeb. dem. Euan. l. 1. c. 6.</note> This cauſed <hi>Euſebius</hi> to ſay <hi>(Soluta est confestim omnis Moſi conſtitutio &amp;c.)</hi> 
               <q>The whole conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Moſes</hi> forthwith was diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and all things of the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whatſoeuer till then reſerued, they then were taken away.</q> From this day, <hi>Ezekiels</hi> new city was to be builded. The lowe Ieruſalem was to giue place vnto that new one, which th'apoſtle termeth<note n="“" place="margin">Gala 4.26 ſo vnderſtood of Luther, Caluine, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iorat, Hemin gius. Hyperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, &amp; others. See Hebr. 12.22.</note> 
               <hi>heauenly and free,</hi> yea the mother of vs all: and by <hi>Iohn</hi> defined to be the<note n="“" place="margin">Concilium Senoſenſe in primo decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth ſo of Reuel. 21.</note> Tabernacle of God reſiant with men. Of the old citie excellent things were ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:184222:14"/> but greater and more meruai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous things are recorded of this city, the ſubſtantiall city of God. And no maruayle, ſeeing this is compact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in ſuch durable manner of ſuch durable matter, as one with God it muſt continue for euer. Th'other was but <hi>Leah,</hi> that is, <hi>Rahel,</hi> the beu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the nations: and better then the Egyptian Queene may bee called<note n="*" place="margin">In Dan. 11 17. ſhe is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Bath-Naſim.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Cleopatra,</hi> the glory of a countrey: for the King of kings hath vnited her to himſelfe for euer. Heereof a certaine Auncient he thus writeth: The citty of our Sauiour is builded. <q>And the Name of that Citty ſhall not be (as was the firſt) <hi>Ieruſhalem</hi> (interpreted <hi>Viſion of Peace,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Ierom here on:</hi> Vrbs Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uatoris ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tructa eſt. &amp;c.</note>) but <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donaj-ſama</hi> (Ierom vſeth <hi>Adonaj</hi> for <hi>Iehouah,</hi> according to the maner of the Hebrues) which in latine ſpeach is turned <hi>Dominus ibidem:</hi> who will neuer departe from it, as from the firſt people he did, ſaying to his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples (<hi>Iohn</hi> 14. <hi>vlt.</hi>) Ariſe, let vs go
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:184222:14"/> hence: and vnto the Iewes (<hi>Math.</hi> 23.38.) your houſe ſhall be left de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſart. But this ſhall haue an eternall poſſeſſion, and he himſelf wilbe the poſſeſſion vnto it, promiſing ſo to the ſame diſciples, ſaying: Beholde, I am with you vnto the ende of the world.</q>
               <note place="margin">Ludouic. La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uater. hereon</note> And a later Writer ſpeakes thus: The Citty was foure-ſquare, whereby is ſignified the firmitude of the Church, becauſe it cannot be euerted. Howſoeuer aſſailed, it euer riſeth vp againſt all aſſaults. <hi>Iehouah there.</hi> Out of this citie the Lord will not depart. He will not leaue it as he did the ſynagogue: but in all ages he will be <hi>There,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that in <hi>Math.</hi> 28. I will be with you vnto the end of the world. Briefly then I inferre, <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> that Chriſtians are not to retaine the whole, or any part of Moſes cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall kingdom, in the nature of that ceremonie: <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Secondly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> that the new teſtaments kingdom once
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:184222:15"/> eſtabliſhed, it neuer after can be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally remoued. Theſe two doctrines how they be receued of Romaniſts, Anabaptiſts, Browniſts, &amp;c. I ſhall briefly examine.</p>
            <p>The Romaniſts commaunde in their Church the vſe of ſundry crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (as garments, oyle, water, ſalte, belles, &amp;c.) and, as their Prouinciall Moguntine ſynode affirmeth,<note place="margin">Mogunt. councel held Anno 1549</note> 
               <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiam exorcizandi poteſtatem accepiſſe, &amp;c.</hi> that the Church hath power of coniuring, ſalt, and other creatures, for auerting the diuelles traines, and noyſome peſtilences: ſo (as they write) their Pope Alexander of old vrgeth his holy water from Leuies ceremoniall water: and they from the Aaronicall prieſthoode do vrge garments and other ceremoniall creatures. What muſt their argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments now be?</p>
            <p n="1">1 The Church hath receued po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer no leſſe than the Synagogue, to exorcize creatures for driuing away
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:184222:15"/> Diuelles: or,</p>
            <p n="2">2 Moſes commanded to the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, holy water, holy oyle, holy garments, &amp;c. therefore the church of Chriſt may, or ought alſo ſo to conſecrate and vſe them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I paſſe by their miſconſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Leuiticall ceremonies, who neither were by the Prieſts exorciſed or coniured: nor yet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their conſecration ſet aparte for ſuch ridiculous purpoſes, as to feare away the diuel, driue away peſtilen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, preſerue corne from thunder, &amp;c. Secondly I anſwere, it follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not, that what ceremonies God by Moſes did preſcribe vnto the ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, that theſe muſt of God by Chriſt Ieſus be continued in the new Teſtaments church: for then it ſhould followe, that not onely ſome ceremonies, but all ſhould be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into the Church. But as the Apoſtle ſaith, that Leuiticall or Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remoniall meates, drinkes,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.16, 17.</note> and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:184222:16"/> holydaies, they were but a ſhadow of things to come, the body (or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) whereof was Chriſt, (and therfore had their ſacramentall end in Chriſt) ſo, the ſame Apoſtle ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the obſeruance of Iudaicall ceremonies, <hi>A yoke,</hi> from which Chriſt hath made vs free. And in deed, to retaine theſe Ceremonies, what is it elſe but the rearing againe of the particion wall which ſtood between Iew and Gentile, and ſo conſequently to deny that Meſſiah is come in the fleſh: ſeeing his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance in our nature, it was for the aboliſhment of that particion wall of ceremonies? Wherevpon a certaine Auncient could well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,<note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. de doctr. chriſt. l. 3. c. 9.</note> that after Chriſt by his reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection manifeſted himſelfe to be the freer of vs from the burden of legall ceremonies, he himſelfe and th'apoſtolicall diſcipline deliuered vnto vs <hi>(quaedam pauca pro multis)</hi> a certaine Few for Many, <hi>(ſicuti eſt
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:184222:16"/> Baptiſmi ſacramentum &amp; celebratio corporis &amp; ſanguinis Domini)</hi> as namely the ſacrament of Baptiſme, and the celebration of our Lord his body and bloud. As for Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by presbyterall impoſition of hands, mentioned by him elſewhere for a kinde of<note n="*" place="margin">Aug. contr. Parmen. li. <hi>2</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi> &amp; alibi <hi>So Bucer ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly,</hi> in l. de vi &amp; vſu mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterii. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uin in Inſtit. l <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> ſect <hi>16</hi> &amp; ch <hi>14.</hi> ſect <hi>20.</hi> &amp; ca. <hi>19.</hi> ſect. <hi>28</hi> &amp; <hi>31 So hath</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logia Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanae confeſſ. <hi>graunted by Chemnitius</hi> in exam. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. Concil. <hi>So hath our doctor Bilſon in his perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ca. 9. and 10.</hi>
               </note> ſacrament (and in the new church practiſed preciſely and plentifully by the Apoſtles and Presbyters) he in this place paſſeth by it, becauſe, neither it was a cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie to the whole Church, nor now inſtituted: but an auncient ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſigne continued, whoſe ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation had no end in Chriſts mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtation. For Chriſtians to reuiue the legall ſhadowes, it is but to caſt againe a vaile vpon Moſes, and to hinder vs (as the Iewes are yet hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred) from ſeeing into the ende of things which by Meſſiah are aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. But in very troth, the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts, their coniuring of creatures for driuing away Diuelles, it is ſo farre
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:184222:17"/> from being Moſaicall (much leſſe Chriſtian) as it rather is borrowed from Ethniks, who ſo hoped to pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifie their Daemones: or elſe from Tobits Apocryphall Angell, who taught the fugation of a diuell (by<note place="margin">Archangeli expoſ. in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſ. Miran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dula.</note> 
               <hi>Cabaliſtes</hi> termed <hi>Aſmodeus,</hi> the prowde diuell) and that by vertue of a fume made vpon a fiſhes heart and liuer. The Romaniſtes coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red creatures tending thus (not to ſo reaſonable a woorke, as to reare vp the partition wall againe, but) to a reuiuing of Gentiles idolatrous worſhip: or at beſt, a putting of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite into Rabbinicall blaſphemous figments, to the violation of Meſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs kingdome.</p>
            <p>Nor doth this doctrine any iote help them which contende againſt certaine garments in our church. And why? becauſe ſuch garments are not with vs vrged for Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall or Sacramentall garments: but onely (as is open in our lawe) for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:184222:17"/> and comlineſſe. Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance did put an end, not to the vſing of the creature, but to the vſing of it <hi>So:</hi> that is, from vſing it ſacramentally, figuratiuely, typical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Touching which free vſe of all his creatures, I ſhall haue occaſion to ſpeake more hereafter.</p>
            <p>Touching the Browniſts and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabaptiſts, they would not be thought to bring vs backe againe to Iudaiſme, but iudge of them by this their argument: The Iſraelites in Deut. 12.2. are commaunded to deſtroy all the places wherein the nations ſerued their Gods: therfore all the Temples or churches where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Romaniſts haue ſerued their Images, they are to be deſtroyed. Or thus: It was ſimplie vnlawfull for the Iſraelites to ſacrifice in the high places: therefore ſimply vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for chriſtians to preach or pray in the Temples of Romiſh or Idolatrous chriſtians. By this argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:184222:18"/> they conclude, a nullitie of all diuine woorſhip in our churches: and by the former, a ruinating of them to the earth. And the one and the other is drawen from a ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall commaundement in the lawe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> That the commaundement was morall (and ſo in that kind perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall) it cannot be: Firſt becauſe the deſtruction of ſuch Idoll Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues, it was oppoſed to the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of one peculiar place, which God would chooſe in Iſrael for put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>(Shemó Sham)</hi> his name there. And for this cauſe, <hi>Moſes</hi> preciſely (hauing ſpoken of ſuch vaſtation) he commaunds his people to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire vnto this one place wherein he put his name. So that betweene this one place and the other, there was a flat oppoſition, th'one falling, th'other ſtanding. And therefore the people no longer commaunded to deſtroy the one, then the other ſtood. But this was not to ſtand for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:184222:18"/> euer, therfore the commaundement of deſtroying the other, not morall, nor continuing for euer.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, who knoweth not that the Tabernacle and Temple were figures of the new Teſtaments church? And for that cauſe we are commaunded,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 2. Rom. 12.1. 1. Cor. 3.16. &amp; 6.19.</note> as liuing ſtones to become a ſpirituall houſe, to offer vp our ſelues for a quicke and liuing ſacrifice: and plainly told, that we be the Temple of the holy ghoſt. Now, will they and euery one grant the Tabernacle and Temple to be figures of the new church? Then by proportion it muſt follow, that the former materiall Idoll houſes, they (as was Babylon, Sodome, Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gipt) were figures of the many falſe aſſemblies ſchiſmaticall and hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, that would be oppoſit vnto the catholike body. All which ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſynagogues (or aſſemblies of falſe woorſhippers) were by the ſpirituall Iſrael of god (and ſpecially by their
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:184222:19"/> ſpirituall weapons) to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen and diſſipated: that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily ſo they may returne to the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the Catholike Church. And to this purpoſe, where the twelue Trybes were armed with carnall weapons, the twelue Apoſtles were armed with ſpirituall weapons, whereby they did not caſt downe materiall ſynagogues, but hawtie imaginations of men, and euery thing that was ſpiritually exalted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, admit (which they would haue) that all our Churches had bin reared vp by Antichriſts limbs, and dedicated vnto Idol-worſhip, ſhould it follow, that theſe houſes ſhould be as deep in pollution as theſe that ſerued the Gentiles? The vncircumciſed Nations in <hi>Canaan</hi> had nothing in their woorſhip, but their owne inuentions, altogether ignorant and vnbeleeuing the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of Grace. As for our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:184222:19"/> ſubiected to Romes go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, the written word of God (for the ſubſtance thereof, ſpecially at time of Churches building) it was preached amongſt them: and no doubt a ſeed of God euer amongſt them. Nor was there other place where God had put his Name, for our predeceſſors to repaire vnto, then within the limits of the Romiſh iuriſdiction, in the midſt of which part of the Temple of God, that blaſphemous horne of Rome was after mounted. If the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.2. were moral and perpetuall touching deſtruction of Pagans houſes, it yet followeth not, that the Idolatrized houſes of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, they were aſwell to be torne vp. There is a great difference: firſt betweene the woorſhippers, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly betweene their woorſhips: thirdly, betweene the end they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred their houſes vnto. Except with the Stoiks we held <hi>(Omnia pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:184222:20"/> paria)</hi> that all ſinnes were alike and of equal weight in the ballance; we otherwiſe cannot argumentate thus: The <hi>Pagans</hi> Idolatrie (which is an Idolatrie in the higheſt degree) it was to ſuffer this iudgement: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſtians in any kind of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie are to ſuffer the ſame. The Hebrew that ſtole another Hebrue,<note place="margin">Deut. 24.7. compared with Exod. 22.1. &amp; ch. 22.22.28. &amp;c.</note> and afterwards ſold him, or made marchandize of him, he was to die the death: but he that ſtole an oxe or ſheepe, and ſold it, was only to reſtore it with ſome aduantage. So Adultrie was death; fornication not: and yet both ſin and abuſe of the bodie. Where the aduerſarie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyeth, theſe Churches may be ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the raſing downe, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to ciuill vſage, as for Barnes, Stables, &amp;c. Herein they ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw themſelues: for the law of <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.2. admitted no ſuch ciuill vſe, but without all exception they were to be battred downe. And
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:184222:20"/> thus theſe fellowes will take away our libertie, and giue vs libertie, not according to ſetled Scripture, but their owne vnſetled fancie.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, it ſeemeth not ſimply vnlawfull for Iſraelites to haue ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed, prayed, preached in their hie-places and Idol-houſes. This I col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect from the 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 3. chap. and alſo the 13. chap. (Wherewith may alſo be conſidered Iſraels ſacrificing, &amp; <hi>Samuels</hi> benediction thereof alſo in the hie-places. 1. <hi>Samuel</hi> 9.12, 13, 14.) In the third chap. it is ſaid that <hi>Salomon</hi> ſacrificed and praied in Gibeon the chiefe hie-place. The fact ſeemeth excuſable, becauſe to that day, no houſe was built vnto the name of the Lord. The Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle through age was far ſpent, and therefore the Arke of God his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ſometimes placed in Roumes that might haue been bettred: and yet at this time ſeated in <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And as in ſuch reſpect, the holie
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:184222:21"/> ghoſt ſeemeth to excuſe the matter; ſo in the ſecond place he plainly proteſts, that God in Gibeon ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to <hi>Salomon,</hi> and highlie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted of his praier for wiſedome. Touching preaching in thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the 13. chap. manifeſteth how <hi>A man of God,</hi> (that is, a Prophet or Preacher of God) he commeth to <hi>Bethel:</hi> and there entring into the Idoll temple dedicated by <hi>Ieroboam</hi> vnto a Caluiſh worſhip, he there by the Alter-ſide ſtandeth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth the will of God, againſt that Idol-worſhip and Prieſthood: and this in the face of <hi>Ieroboams</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence. By all which it ſeemeth vnto me, that God, and the people of god, did put a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the houſes which Canaanits reared vp for their Religion ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancially and wholie euill, and theſe places which Idolatrous Iſraelites did reare vp for their linſy-woolſie medley religion. Who (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:184222:21"/> their Idolatrie) were euer intereſſed with Circumciſion, the ſeale of the Couenant, wherby they ſtood a ſeperate people from the Heathen: and ſtill amongſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall menaces, they had this Euangelical ſpeach from the mouth of God, <hi>Iſrael my people.</hi> Which (if the former law in <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.2. were moral) ſhould teach vs a great diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent vſe betweene <hi>Pagans</hi> temples, and Idolatrized Churches: yea, though the Chriſtians were ſo deep in Schiſme &amp; Idolatrie, as it ſhould be vnlawfull for <hi>Iudah</hi> in ſuch their eſtate, to ioyne fully in ſpirituall communion with <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, where they teach that we can haue no ſpiritual vſe of the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes which Antichriſt or Romaniſts haue Idolatrized, they forget how the Temple was vſed for God his worſhip, ſundrie times after it had been horribly prophaned. If they replie, we except not againſt ſuch
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:184222:22"/> houſes ſimplie for hauing been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned, but for hauing been dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated from the very foundation to Idolatrie: I demaund of them, firſt how it doth appeare in <hi>Deut.</hi> 12 that the <hi>Iſraëlites</hi> were tyed to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, whether all ſuch places had been ſo dedicated from the verie foundation? Secondly, I would know of them, how they know that all our Churches were founded by Romes Apoſtacie to that Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous woorſhip? Here they muſt make a religion of it, to ſearch after the ages of Churches: and whether they were builded ſince Anti-chriſt was mounted. Here I will help the Nouices. <hi>Diocleſian</hi> deſtroyed the Temples,<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. 8. cap. 2.</note> as <hi>Euſebius</hi> recordeth (ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie aged were theſe Churches) and then the Gentiles vpbraided the Chriſtians (ſaith<note place="margin">Orig. ad Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum l. 4. &amp; Arnob. l. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Origen</hi>) with their lacke of Temples: as now they might well laugh vs to ſcorne, if we would pull down our Churches for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:184222:22"/> ſatisfaction of Browniſts, who ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer are like to build a Church: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyers (ſomuch as in them is) both of Churches materiall and ſpiritual. The former loſſe by <hi>Diocleſian</hi> was recouered by the edict of <hi>Galerius Maximinus,</hi> after the hand of God had been ſharp vpon him: as<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. 8. c. 16. &amp; 9. ch. 10. Niceph. l. 7. c. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius</hi> and <hi>Nicephorus</hi> witneſſe. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, how bountifull <hi>Conſtantinus Magnus</hi> was this way, th'eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call hyſtories ſufficiently vtter. Nor was this of Conſtantine effected ſo late as 340. yeeres from our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours incarnation. Now let our Church-ruinors teach vs, Firſt, when Antichriſt had ſubdued our Weſterne parts vnto him, ſo that thence-forth all ſtood ſubiects to that Beaſt? Secondly, let them proue vnto vs that our Churches in ſuch and ſuch times of Antichriſt, they were builded at his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, and by his members, vnto his apoſtaticall woorſhip.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:184222:23"/>
            <p>Sixtly, admit that Antichriſt, and whoſoeuer had reared vp and dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated our Temples to idoles, yet the creature recouered out of their handes, it ceaſeth not to be the good creature of God.<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.4, 5</note> For the Apoſtle teacheth me, that euery creature of God is good, and nothing ought to bee refuſed, if it be receiued with thankeſgiuing: and reaſon heereof he thus rendreth, <hi>Becauſe it is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by the word and praier.</hi> If no meat entring into me (though once vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane by the Lawe) can now pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute the beleeuer; much leſſe can garments and houſes that are crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures externall and outward. The Apoſtle indeede ſaith, that in not touching, taſting, handling ſuch things as the Law once counted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2</note> 
               <hi>it hath a ſhew of wiſedome,</hi> but in trueth no ſubſtance of wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. And for that cauſe he calleth it no better then <hi>Ethelo-threskeia, A will-worſhip:</hi> whereas (if we be riſen
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:184222:23"/> with Chriſt) then wee will vſe our Chriſtian liberty in the free vſe of God his creatures; &amp; not bring our ſelues backe into a Iudaicall bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.<note place="margin">Iohn 4.20 21. &amp;c.</note> Hereof the woman of Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria coulde not be ignorant, who by our Sauiour himſelfe was taught, that not in <hi>Iaakobs</hi> mountaine, nor yet in <hi>Beniamins</hi> hilles, was Gods worſhip or ſacrifice to bee longer ſeated: but the houre was comming, and euen then was (begunne) for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boliſhing that forme of ſacrifice, as alſo the Place. And hitherto Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had relation, when hee writeth thus vnto <hi>Timothy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 2.8</note> 
               <hi>I will therefore that the men pray euery where, lifting vp pure hands without wrath or doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</hi> Becauſe fooliſh man hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated Creatures to the patronage of this or that true or falſe Saint, I muſt therfore abhorre the creature, ſpecially in eccleſiaſticall or ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vſage. By this crooked rule, I may not preach nor pray in <hi>England,</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:184222:24"/> becauſe it was dedicated to Saint <hi>George:</hi> nor in <hi>Wales,</hi> becauſe <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> is there made patrone: nor in <hi>Ireland,</hi> by reaſon of Saint <hi>Patricke:</hi> nor in <hi>Scotland,</hi> bicauſe of Saint <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew:</hi> nor in <hi>Fraunce,</hi> becauſe of S. <hi>Denys:</hi> nor in any countrey where Rome hath domineerd, becauſe all is dedicated to ſomewhat. Nay, I muſt in no one day of the yeare preach or pray: becauſe they haue to euery day giuen a Saint. Thus, if a man deſire to runne himſelfe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a labyrinth and endleſſe Maze, let him but leape into the Browniſts and Anabaptiſts faction. This ſhal ſuffice for manifeſtation of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Doctrine: namely, <hi>That Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are not to retayne the whole, or any part of Moſes Ceremoniall kingdome, in the nature of Ceremony.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="sermon">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:184222:24"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Second Sermon.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecond generall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine <hi>[That the newe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staments king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome once e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stabliſhed, it can neuer bee totally remooued]</hi> that remaineth in the next place to be further cleered. And that by the grace of God ſhall be done; firſt, by obſeruing the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference betwixt vs and the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts (we both holde the Church e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer viſible: but they in one forme,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:184222:25"/> we in another:) ſecondly, by exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining the Arrians, Anabaptiſts, and Browniſts allegations: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they would haue the Church for very many yeares, to haue no Face, or viſibilitie at all.</p>
            <p>Touching the diſcrepance twixt Romaniſts and vs, it lieth heerein: they hold, that the new Teſtaments church once generally planted, the face thereof continueth euermore gloriouſly viſible. And to this end they alledge diuers places (ſpecially out of the prophets) which doe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre a large and glorious face of Chriſt and his kingdome here. We of the other ſide, doe teach, that this new church (howſoeuer in her firſt plantation by the Apoſtles, it was both paſſing large and glorious) yet in ſucceeding times, it wained with the Moone, ſhee loſt much of her glory, and of her outſtretched viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie. And to this purpoſe wee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, firſt, the ſtate of Iſraels church
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:184222:25"/> as a tipe and figure thereof: ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, very many ſcriptures (old &amp; new) which can admit no other collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: laſtly, we vrge experience it ſelf.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">I. Type.</note> touching the Type or Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, we ſee the church of Iſrael go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out with banners in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and finally ſeated in glorious Canaan by <hi>Ioſhuah.</hi> After his death al ranne out of order, the vncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed had them long in ſubiection, there was no king in Iſrael, and eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man didde what was good in his owne eyes. Then in <hi>Saul, Dauid,</hi> &amp; <hi>Solomons</hi> times, we ſee the church by ſundry ſteps mounted &amp; enlarged: but in <hi>Rehoboams</hi> dayes wee ſee ten tribes ſchiſme from the twoo (that is, from <hi>Iudah</hi> and <hi>Beniamin</hi>) and that which was worſe, didde reare vp and woorſhippe; firſt, calues in Dan and Bethel: ſecondly, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alim with his abhominations. Nor was the bodie of theſe tenne tribes at anie tyme recouered, but fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:184222:26"/> in <hi>Hoſheahs</hi> raigne, carried away by the Aſſyrian armie: Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonies of ſtraungers beeing in their rowme tranſported vnto theyr Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tropolitane Citie Samaria and them parts.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, the little king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>Iudah</hi> (contayning alſo <hi>Beniamin</hi>) it did not euer retayne the face of her orderly gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for ſundrie of the Kinges brought Idolatrie in: but by others agayne in ſome good ſorte purged. Yet finally (ſuch was the height of their ſinne) GOD left them to the boyling potte of the North (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to Nebuchadnetzar) who ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led their Cittie and Temple, and departed the chiefe of the Royall ſeede vnto <hi>Babel.</hi> Then for ſeuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares did orderly ſacrifice ceaſe, their Iudiciall pollicie (giuen by God at mount Sinai, ſo well as the eccleſiaſticall) it was ſubiected to the pleaſure of ſtraungers, then
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:184222:26"/> where was their beauteous Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution? And at the end of ſeauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty yeares, Babels Monarch was ſubiected to the Medes and Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, who licenced <hi>Iudah</hi> to returne for building their Cittie and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: which after ſome nine and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie yeares were reedified, but where was the ſacramentall Arke of God his preſence? Where was Moſes originall copie? Where was <hi>Vrim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> for deciſion of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie ſcruples? What was become of Aarons rod and the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentall Manna? And that which was not leaſt, what became of their Iudiciall pollicie, from that time vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Chriſt Ieſus? Somewhat I know there was, but farre from the firſt patterne. Curtailed they were of their Moſaicall conſtitutions: Firſt by <hi>Babels</hi> monarch: ſecondly, by that of Medes and Perſians: thirdly, by the Greekes <hi>Alexander:</hi> fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by the two legged gouernement
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:184222:27"/> of <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Syria,</hi> ſpringing out of the third Monarch: and laſtly, by that laſt Monarch Rome (ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing vp the former togither with <hi>Meſſiahs</hi> appearance) who had ſo manacled <hi>Iudah,</hi> that they coulde not condemne <hi>Ieſus,</hi> but by the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie of wicked Rome. This being the condition of the typical church, it followeth (ſay we) that the New-teſtaments-church be in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure thereto analogized. And then onely it is ſo, when we find after her fulneſſe of grace, a declining there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: running into ſchiſmes and deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate apoſtacies: whereby God is prouoked to leſſen her light, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh her glory, to ouer-turne her conſtitution, to abbreuiate her pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Scripture. II.</note>Secondly, the ſcriptures which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre ſuch lamentable ruine of the church, they be many: wherof a few, &amp; to this purpoſe pregnant. That 89. pſalme is a typicall prophecie of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:184222:27"/> Chriſt &amp; his kingdome, who grants not? wherein wee firſt ſee a glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous large kingdom giuen to Chriſt for his poſſeſsion, but anon, behold (as grieued at his <hi>Meſſiah</hi> or vncted, who hath ſinne conſidered as <hi>vpon</hi> him, but <hi>in</hi> his members) he caſteth his crown on the ground, he breaks downe his walles, ruinates his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treſſes, and leaues him to be ſpoyled &amp; rebuked of the multitude. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the learned monke <hi>Folengius</hi> thus writeth: <hi>Theſe things may be applyed to the Christians times, and perchance to our preſent times.</hi> Preſently wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon he plainely ſaith, that <hi>Religion</hi> is conculcate and trode vnderfoote. And <hi>Aben-ezra</hi> citeth a certayne Spaniſh Iew ſo amazd at this pſalm (for the Iews dreame,<note place="margin">Io. Baptiſta Fol. in pſa. <hi>89 40.</hi> Ad chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianorum tempora (for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanque prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentia) aptari poſſunt.</note> that <hi>Meſſiahs</hi> kingdome ſhoulde be according to the worlds glory, &amp; ſo perpetuall) as he refuſed to reade it: euen as the Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maniſts at this day can not abide to hear, or reade any thing that croſſes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:184222:28"/> their Iudaicall opinion touching the outward face of Meſſiahs king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Nor maruell I thereat, ſeeing heere in the perſon of <hi>Aetham</hi> (brought in by the holy Ghoſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulating the cauſe of ſuch down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fall) wee are taught howe hardely our nature brooketh the caſt-down eſtate of Meſſiahs outward glorie. Another Scripture wee haue in the foure and twentieth of <hi>Mathew,</hi> whereas our Sauior euidently fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telleth the notable intricate eſtate of the faithfull in after times: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that many falſe chriſts, falſe apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, falſe prophets, ſhoulde ariſe in the church, to the ſeduction of many; charitie growing colde, and iniquitie hauing the vpper hande. Yea, heerewithall, that ſeduction and deluſion (as in the ſecond E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of Paul to the Theſſalonians and the ſecond chapter) ſhould be ſo ſtrong, that if it were poſſible, the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:184222:28"/> very elect of God ſhoulde be ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced.</p>
            <p>This generalitie of falſe prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, of horrible iniquitie, and migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie deluſion, it can not ſtand with a notable and glorious viſibilitie of the Church: nor yet can be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered where the conſtitution and pollicie is (as at firſt) ſounde and vnſhaken. Nay it argueth (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of Saint Paul in 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3. and 2. <hi>Timoth.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, &amp;c. and that of Saint <hi>Peter</hi> 1. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle 2.1, &amp;c.) that all ſhall lie in horrible confuſion and diſorder, do the holy men of GOD what they can. Which alſo is denoted by the<note n="*" place="margin">This I haue mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted largely in my Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doton. Hieron. in Zeph. 1.12 <hi>Recte aeutem Ieruſhalem. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> parable of tares, <hi>Math</hi> 13.24, &amp;c Touching which firſt and latter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate of the Church, hearken what Ierome writeth on <hi>Zephaniah,</hi> 1. <hi>Chronic.</hi> verſe 12. <q>
                  <hi>I will ſearch Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalem</hi> with candles] <hi>Rightly Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhalem,</hi> that is, the church which firſt was called <hi>Iebus,</hi> that is, trode
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:184222:29"/> vnder foote. Becauſe it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culcate of the Gentiles, and was a laughing ſtocke to the Deuils, it was called <hi>Iebus.</hi> And after the peace of the Lord began to dwell in it, and his place made in peace, it was called <hi>Ieruſhalem.</hi> But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the laſt-times (as I haue oft ſaid) Charitie ſhall freeze, and Iniquitie ſhall be multiplied, (yea the light of the Sun ſhall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from <hi>Ieruſhalem,</hi> and the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation ſhall be ſo great, that the verie elect of God ſhall hardlie be ſaued) the Lord therefore then with the Lanthorne of his word and Reaſon will ſearch all the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>Ieruſhalem,</hi> and bring them into ſight.</q> 
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Another plaine ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture we haue in <hi>Reuel.</hi> 6. where af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our Salomon hath rid foorth vpon the cleere word of Truth,<note place="margin">Pſ. 45.4.</note> and Meeknes, and Iuſtice, and by the bowe of his right hand hath ſubdued a people vnto him: We
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:184222:29"/> preſently after ſee bloodie perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſcarſitie, death, ſlaughter, together with a fearfull darkning of the Sunne, blood ſtayning the Moone, accompanied with a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Apoſtacie of the Church-ſtarres from the kingdome of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto earthly conuerſation, ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecting therewith a generall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of all good order. All which thinges can be but myſtically vnderſtood according to the nature of prophecie, and ſo a plaine decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the Church turned vpſide downe, with a loſſe of her large vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilitie and glorie. Other Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures may of Romaniſtes be held more litigious, theſe ſhall here ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</p>
            <p>Beſides the type and plaine eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Scripture,<note place="margin">III Experience.</note> I will adde the argument of experience ſigned by Antiquitie. For the firſt 300. yeeres and better after Chriſtes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, we are not ignorant
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:184222:30"/> of a reaſonable glorious eſtate of the Church, for the which ſome haue (not altogether vnfitly) vrged that of the Apocryphall <hi>Eſdras,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Eſd. 7.28.29.</note> (a thing that he might geſſe at by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of Scripture) where in the <hi>perſon of the Lord he ſaith:</hi> 
               <q>My ſonne Ieſus ſhall appeare (with theſe that be with him) and they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine ſhall reioyce with him <hi>400.</hi> yeeres. After theſe yeeres ſhall my ſon Christ dye, and all men that haue life:</q> as if he ſhould ſay, Chriſt ſhall liue in his Church 400. yeeres, then ſhal he dye, and the Church be darkned. And indeed, for ſo long we find the writers giuing in a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent teſtimonie, then for the 200. yeeres after. But after 600. yeeres (or there abouts) I trow that by one litle horne ſtarting vp at Rome, and an other in the Eaſt (vniuerſall <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Machomet,</hi> both affirming they haue the kaies of Paradiſe, and ſpeaking well of <hi>Ieſus</hi> in generall
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:184222:30"/> tearmes) a foule beaſt was moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that opened a bottomles pit of humane inuentions that darkened all.<note place="margin">Sozomen. eccl. hiſt. l. 6. c. 5.</note> Anthonie the Heremite (about the beginning of <hi>Conſtantines</hi> raign, he is ſaid to ſee in a dream certaine Mules <hi>[Altare inſultantes calcibus &amp;c.]</hi> leaping vpon the Altare with their feete, and ouerturning the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred table: whereupon he ſhould ſay, that by mixt and adulterate do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and by rebellion of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes the Church ſhould be harmed. And indeed (not long after) <hi>Arriani potiti ſunt Eccleſiarum gubernaculis,</hi> the abhominable Arrians got the Churches reines in their hands. <q>Yea (ſaith venerable <hi>Beda</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bedae eccl. hiſt. de gent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Angl. l. 1. c. 9.</note>) Peace was in the Church vntill the times of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> his frenzie, which <hi>(corrupto orbe toto)</hi> the whole world being there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with corrupted, did alſo with the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nome of his errour, infect this Iland of <hi>Britaine</hi> ſo far remoued out of the world. And this (as againe he after
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:184222:31"/> vrgeth) notwithſtanding it was condemned in the Synode of Nice.</q> If Arrianiſme ſo quickely got ſuch an vniuerſall head, what did alſo <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius, Macedonius, Neſtorius, Marti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and all other heretikes their doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine? All of them marching in bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell aray againſt the Church; all of them termed by <hi>Chryſoſtoms</hi> Riuall on Mat. 24.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Incertus an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> on Mat. 84.</note> the army abhominable in the midſt of the Temple, prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a ſeate for Antichriſt. Ech of theſe wonne diſciples, did drawe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and teare the vnſeamed coat of Ieſus in a thouſand peeces. Not long after wee finde a man of ſinne mounted in the midſt of Gods tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, aduancing himſelfe as a god, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting himſelfe aboue the thinges of God, treading chriſtian kings vnder foote, and ſubduing all to his luſtes, as the apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and S. <hi>Iohn</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uidently fore-prophecied.<note place="margin">Clem. Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andr. in ſtro. lib. 1. fol. 2.</note> If <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens</hi> could ſay of the churches next ſucceeding the Apoſtles, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:184222:31"/> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Few children like the Fathers (for few conuaied the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine vncorrupted) what may we ſay of the doctrine and churches e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate in times long after? euen that which Ierome long ſince ſaid:
<q>
                  <l>— Inter Nitentia culta,</l>
                  <l>Lappae<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> et tribuli et ſteriles domina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur Auenae<note place="margin">Ierome a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Luciſerians.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Burres, thiſtles, and wilde-oates,</l>
                  <l>Domineere in midſt of the wheate field</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To ſpare the repetition of odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous particulars, Experience hath taught vs, how the wheate field (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome ſleepineſſe of Miniſters) it became ſo peſtred with viſible and incurable tares, that hardely anie wheate could be ſeene. The Lord his vineyard became ſo clogged with thornes and briars, that hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly any Vine coulde bee diſcerned. The Barne floore was ſo full of chaffe, that the Grayne was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt inuiſible. The holie man Iob was ſcabs from the crowne of
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:184222:32"/> the head vnto the ſoule of the foote, he ſate vpon aſhes ſcraping himſelf with a potſhard, his breath was cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, his friends could hardly know him: but yet not deſtitute of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpirit, of a good conſcience. The Church indeed was in Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, ſubiected vnto Babels externall gouernment: but with <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the three yong gentlemen of <hi>Iudah,</hi> it preſerued a good conſcience. The yeeres of captiuitie expyred, it coms forth of <hi>Babel</hi> in a great meaſure, but without expectation of the former Apoſtolicall glory. Yong-men wil think the laſt Temple ſuperexcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, but Aged ſpirited-ones will weep, at the inferioritie thereof, in compariſon of the firſt. Diuers yet with Daniel bide behind in <hi>Babel,</hi> which ſomtimes come to their graue in peace: ſomtimes do buckle with Lyons, and depart to heauen in a firie chariot with <hi>Elijah.</hi> So far are we (whatſoeuer the Romaniſtes
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:184222:32"/> barke) from condemning all our predeceſſors, or yet adiudging to Hell, all ſuch as liue and dye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. For as there be in our Church, who are not verily of it; ſo we beleeue there be many in their idolatrous Iſraell, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding are not verily of it. Thus briefly I haue cleered, that notwithſtanding the Church hath been euer viſible, yet ſhe hath ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times (as alſo her <hi>Figure</hi>) been ſpoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of her glory, darkned in her members, captiued of her aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, deſtitute of her conſtitution. Now remaineth it I examine the reaſons of ſuch aduerſaries as deny the Church alwayes to haue been viſible.</p>
            <p>The Arrians, Anabaptiſts, and Browniſts, gone out of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like communion, they oppoſe to the Church her euer viſibilitie thus: Firſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the typicall Church was not euer viſible. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, direct ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:184222:33"/> teſtifie that the new-Church ſhould not be euer viſible.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For probation of the firſt, they ſay that the Church was not viſible in <hi>Elias</hi> his time: and to that purpoſe they alleage the Prophets com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt Iſraell, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.2, 1. <hi>Kings</hi> 19. Whereto I anſwere: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, it is an ill ſhaped forme of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoning to ſay, <hi>Elias</hi> ſaw no Church, therfore no church was any where viſible: <hi>Elias</hi> ſaw no church in Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, therefore there was no church viſible there, nor yet in <hi>Iudah.</hi> It is a ſophiſtication of this nature, <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> ſeeth not, therefore <hi>Peter</hi> ſeeth not: There is no light here, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no where. Secondly, I anſwer: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Elias</hi> did not ſo reaſon: for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint was not againſt <hi>Iudah</hi> (wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he knew that the Church then floriſhed vnder good <hi>Iehoſophat)</hi> but againſt Iſrael the ten ſchiſmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Trybes, where then he feared that bloody <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Ieſabell</hi> had
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:184222:33"/> ſlaughtred all, from whoſe furie he then fled. But the Prophets aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is corrected of the Lord ſaying, that he had reſerued 7000 ſoules which bowed no knee (that is, did not outward ſubſtantial homage) to <hi>Baal.</hi> And indeed, if we conſider (beſides theſe Prophets which <hi>Oba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diah</hi> hid in caues) the ſundry ſchools of Prophets at <hi>Elias</hi> his time of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing rapt vp, we may eaſily beleeue that God had a notable people in that ſchiſmaticall Iſraell: ſeeing he ſendeth not forth many prophets, but when he is minded to gather in ſome large Harueſt. Thirdly, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> we can by plaine demonſtration, poynt foorth the Churches viſibility, from the verie firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> vnto Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam.</hi> In the houſes of
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Adam</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Sheth</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 <hi>Enoſh</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Kainan</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Mahalaleel</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Iered</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 <hi>Henoch,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Theſe 10. ſee in Gen. 1.3. &amp;c.</note>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Methuſhelah</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9 <hi>Lamech</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10 <hi>Noach,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:184222:34"/> The Church was viſible in them till the floud. After the floud, the Church ſtretched it ſelfe thorough the houſes of Noach,
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>Shem</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>Arphaxad</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <note place="margin">Theſe ten ſee in Gen. 11.10. &amp;c.</note>3 <hi>Selah</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Heber</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>5 <hi>Peleg</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>6 <hi>Reu</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>7 <hi>Serug</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>8 <hi>Nachor</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>9 <hi>Thara</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>10 <hi>Abram</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>From Abram to the captiuitie of Babel, and from thence vnto Ieſus, Saint Mathew draweth a direct line in three times foureteene Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that is, two and fortie, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the number of Iſraels ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or pitching places mentioned in the booke of Numbers chapt. 33. As for Saint Luke, hee in his third chapt doth point out the firſt fruits of God, from the firſt Adam vnto the ſecond. Saint <hi>Mathew</hi> from <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> dooth, vnto the captiuitie, paſſe through the houſe of <hi>Solomon</hi> his el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſonne, finiſhing this mans ſeed in <hi>Iehoiachin:</hi> from the front of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:184222:34"/> whoſe name <hi>Iehouah</hi> remoueth<note place="margin">Compare 2. King. 24.6. with Ier. 22.24.28. &amp;c. according to Greek for me Ieconias in Math. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>Iah,</hi> (as a ſignet from his finger, terming him <hi>Coniah</hi>) pulling heerewith <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than</hi> (the other ſonne of <hi>Dauid</hi>) his family into the line by adoption: beginning with <hi>Salathiel,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Zerubbabel:</hi> and then downe by his eldeſt ſonne <hi>Abiud,</hi> vnto Chriſt. S. <hi>Luke</hi> beginning with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> (the ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſed father of Ieſus) hee ſteppeth vpwarde to <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> by the line of his ſecond ſonne <hi>Rheſa:</hi> and ſo from him directly vpward to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid:</hi> not by <hi>Solomons</hi> houſe, which ended with the captiuitie, but by <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thans</hi> line, the line of adoption. This paines haue the two Euangeliſts ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, for manifeſting the church her viſibilitie, from the beginning of the worlde, vnto Meſſiahs comming. The Typicall church ſo ouerturn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth our aduerſaries doctrine: for that was alwayes viſible.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they alleadge certaine ſcriptures againſt the new churches
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:184222:35"/> viſibilitie: the ſeeming ſtrongeſt whereof be theſe: firſt, <hi>Reuelat.</hi> 12. where, by the woman, they truely vnderſtand the church (whereof the virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was an arch-member) and from her lodging in the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe for a time, two times, and halfe a time, they vnderſtand ſome long time, wherein the church ſhould be hid from the ſight of al, be inuiſible. I anſwer, ſcripture muſt be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from ſcripture, not by vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable fancies: for, where haue they any one ſcripture, which <hi>By being in the wilderneſſe</hi> doth vnderſtand <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſibilitie?</hi> Rather lette them vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the holy-ghoſt puttes vs hereby in mind of the ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> fed in the wilderneſſe, and (as Moſes ſayth <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.4. <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.11.) carried as vpon the wings of an Eagle: a figure of the worlds ſtate, through which the Church heere is to paſſe, in her pilgrimage ſpirituall.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:184222:35"/>
            <p>Now, who will ſay, that <hi>Iſrael</hi> was inuiſible in the wilderneſſe? Or that they could be conſidered, but onely according to ſecret Election? The flat contrary followeth. Such ill happe haue theſe men in their al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation of ſcripture. Another ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is that before alleadged in <hi>Reu.</hi> 6. whence they would conclude an apoſtacie of the whole church. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer again, ſcripture muſt expound ſcripture. Compare this wyth <hi>Iſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ahs</hi> prophecie chapt. 24. laſt verſe: as alſo with 34. chap and 4. verſe, &amp; with other like places, and it onely implyeth, a darke deſolation of all church beauty, and orderly conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution: whereby God teſtifieth his anger againſt rich and poore, one &amp; an other. The Moone therefore is ſeene coloured like blood, whereby each meaneth a general perſecution and blodſhed in the church: which cannot be, if the church were inuiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. And to this purpoſe, marke
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:184222:36"/> howe in the twelfth chapter, when the red dragon aſſayled the Church wyth all his might, hee yet drewe downe but a third parte of the ſtars, ſome were reſerued to ſhine in the Church: God euer in that reuelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhewing mercy to a remnant, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwiſe the viols of his wrath were powred out vpon the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant multitude. This theyr winde ſhaketh therfore no hauer. Another ſcripture is, <hi>Reu.</hi> 13. where (ſay they) all do take the beaſts mark. Tis vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true, for the holy-ghoſt thus ſayth: <hi>All that dwell vppon the earth ſhall worſhippe him</hi> (marke the exception) <hi>whoſe names are not written in the Booke of the life of the Lambe, &amp;c.</hi> And becauſe ſuch there ſhall be, he afterwardes concludeth, <hi>Here is the patience of the Saynts.</hi> So that Saints there ſhall be, who wyth patience ſhall conquere. And that is more plainely declared in the 11. chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where all the tyrannous raigne
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:184222:36"/> of the beaſt (chooſe whether that beaſt be the body of cruell Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, or the ſonne of perdition) GOD alſo hath his Prophetes, by whoſe miniſterie, the oyle of God, his ſauing grace is conueyed vnto his people.</p>
            <p>Thus theſe men talke (no men ſo much) of the booke of <hi>Reuelation,</hi> before any one of the Seales be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claſped vnto them. They ſhould now at laſt learne to meddle leſſe with this booke, ſeeing the holy ghoſt leaueth ſo fearfull a curſe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe that adde their owne idle fancies therto, <hi>Reu.</hi> 22.19. An o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſcripture they alleage, namely, 2. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. whence they affirme the Churches whole departure from the Faith. I anſwere: Firſt the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient writers did ordinarily vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand<note place="margin">Ierom ad Algaſiam. Tertull. de reſurrect. ca. 24. Auguſt. de ciuitat. l. 20.</note> it of a generall <hi>Reuolt</hi> from Romes Empire, which then had ruledome ouer the Nations of the earth. And that indeed is verie
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:184222:37"/> plainly fore-told by <hi>S. Iohn</hi> in <hi>Reuel.</hi> 17.16. Later writers (in reſpect of ſome after circumſtances) do take it to be an Apoſtacie generall from Faith: but none that ſtinke not of hereſie, do from thence conclude a flat Nullitie of the Church. A ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall deſolation there ſhould be (as before in the <hi>Reuel.</hi>) but not a fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling away in euery particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. For this is an abſurd forme of argumentation: <hi>Many</hi> (or, <hi>the moſt</hi>) ſhall fall away: <hi>therefore euery one ſhall fall away.</hi> The man of ſin with his army abhominable ſhould enter into this new Citie and Temple of God (yea, rather riſe vp in the midſt thereof) ſowing his perfidious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and planting his Idolatrous bottomles pit-inuentions, but yet neuer eſſentially ſubdue thoſe ſoules vnto him, whoſe names were writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Lambs booke. Spot them he might with many ſuperſtitions, but neuer ſubuert them in the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:184222:37"/> of their Faith and Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: as<note place="margin">In my Antid. as alſo in my Viſible Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian.</note> elſ where I haue in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting plainlie euinced. If during Antichriſts raigne there ſhould be no viſible people of God, then An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſhould be no more Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, ſeeing Chriſt had none in oppoſition againſt him. Anti-chriſt muſt euer haue ſome to warre a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt: and there muſt euer be ſome to wage battaile againſt Antichriſt. Otherwiſe fire would drop from Heauen, and the world thereupon be preſently conſumed: ſeeing there were none in the earth who had the word of Couenant in their mouths. Such Nouices are ignorant of the promiſe ſealed by the Father vnto <hi>Meſſiah</hi> the Churches <hi>Redeemer.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 59.21.</note> 
               <hi>My ſpirit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that is vpon thee, and my words which I haue put in thy mouth, ſhal not depart out of thy mouth, nor out of the mouth of thy ſeed, nor out of thy ſeedes-ſeed, ſaith Iehouah, from henceforth euen for E<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ER.</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:184222:38"/> And to this purpoſe (when the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred<note place="margin">Reu. 7.1. &amp;c.</note> winds of God breathed by the <hi>foure Euangeliſts</hi> were to be held back in an vnknowen tongue) the Lord taketh order for many Iewes, and moe Gentiles: that they ſhould notwithſtanding carie (not onely in their heart, but alſo in their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heads) the viſible marke of true Chriſtianitie.<note place="margin">Bulling part. 2. in annot. tabulae 5.</note> 
               <q>
                  <hi>Bullinger</hi> in his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of times (hauing ſpoken of the moſt accurſed times wherein <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes, Saduces, Eſſeni,</hi> crept into the Iewiſh Church) he addeth: <hi>Interim non dubium eſt &amp;c.</hi> Meane time it is not to be doubted, that true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine continued vncorrupted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the litle remnant of Gods people. For <hi>Simon Iustus</hi> (called alſo <hi>Hillels</hi> ſon or diſciple) and <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charie</hi> Iohn Baptiſts father, as alſo the Elders of our Sauiour (ſo well as others whoſe names are vnknowen) they conſerued (doubtles) the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of religion: not bowing their
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:184222:38"/> knees to the traditionary and ſecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie <hi>Baal.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The laſt times of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dahs church is a type of our times.</note> For in all times the Lorde reſerued to himſelfe a Church: yea, in the midſt of hereſies, ſchiſmes &amp; corruptions. And them times were a type of theſe our laſt times, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in at this day we liue.</q> In which pad of <hi>Bullinger, Caluine, Peter Martir,</hi> &amp; al of any note in theſe latter times do vniformely walke. This poynt I will (to the ſhame of hereticall Chriſtians) ſhutte vp with <hi>Sybillaes</hi> prophecie.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Sed poſtquam Roma<note place="margin">Sybil. l. 2.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Aegyptum reget, imperio<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </l>
               <l>Froenabit, ſummi</l>
               <l>tum ſumma potentia Regni</l>
               <l>Regis inextincti</l>
               <l>mortalibus exorietur.</l>
               <l>Rex etenim ſanctus</l>
               <l>veniet, quitotius Orbis</l>
               <l>Omnia ſeclorum</l>
               <l>per tempora ſceptra tenebit.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Wherein ſhe plainely affirmeth, that after <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall rule ouer <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:184222:39"/> (and that it did preſently after <hi>Herods</hi> creation of King for <hi>Iudaea</hi>) a moſt high King (namely <hi>Meſſiah</hi>) ſhould ſet vp a kingdome ouer the whole world, whoſe kingdome ſhal haue no end. In the ſecond place, ſo this ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d doctrine is clered, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>That the New-testaments King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome once establiſhed, it neuer after can be totally remooued.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nowe it remayneth we conſider more particularly this ſame Cittie: and that is doone by ſearching out; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> firſt, what is the Citties foundation: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> then in the next place, who bee the Citizens.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The foundation of this City (that is, of this Church) it is, firſt, Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; ſecondly, Reall. Perſonall, as the Church is ſayd to be built vpon ſome perſon or perſons: Reall, as it is ſaid to be built vpon ſome Thing or matter. The foundation perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall is two-folde: firſt, as it is built vpon Chriſt: ſecondly, vppon the
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:184222:39"/> Apoſtles and Prophets. That Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is the foundation, harken to <hi>Paul</hi> (1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.11.) <hi>Other founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion can no man lay (than that which is laid (which is Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> That the Apoſtles and Prophets are alſo ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Foundation,</hi> harken to the ſame Apoſtle (<hi>Epheſians</hi> chapter 2. verſe 20.) <hi>And ye are built vpon the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of the Apostles and Prophets, Ieſus Christ himſelfe being the chiefe corner ſtone.</hi> Nor is the word foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation expreſſed in both theſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, otherwiſe then by one and the ſame word (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Themélton</hi>) in the original. <hi>Aquinas</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho. Aquin. ſuper 1. Cori. 3.</note> remembreth both theſe, thus: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>num habet per ſe ſoliditatem &amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>The firſt of them hath the ſoliditie of it ſelfe (like as ſome Rock wheron ſome edifice is builded, and vnto this foundation Chriſt Ieſus is reſembled) for he is the Rock ſpoken of in <hi>Math.</hi> 7.24.25. Th'other foundation, it hath the ſoliditie (not of it ſelfe, but) of
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:184222:40"/> the other ſolide ſubiect (like as ſtones which firſt are placed vpon a ſolide Rock, and in this ſenſe the Apoſtles are called the foundation of the Church, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.20. So far the Schoolman.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the foundation <hi>Real,</hi> it is onely the Faith or Goſpell of Chriſt Ieſus, whereon the Church or faithfull are ſaid (often of diuers) to build. And this Goſpell is ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times called <hi>Simply,</hi> the goſpell of God and Chriſt Ieſus (as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.1, 9, 16, and 15, 16, 19, 29, &amp;c.) Sometimes <hi>Respectiuely</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles goſpell, as in <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.16, and 16.25. The Goſpell of God and Chriſt Ieſus it is, as they are the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors therof: but the Apoſtles goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, as they are the Preachers ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. Both theſe ſenſes of foundation remembred, let vs come to examine the <hi>Romaniſtes</hi> on the one hand: and then the <hi>Browniſts</hi> on the other hand.</p>
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:184222:40"/>
            <p>The Romaniſts from theſe words in Matth. 16.18. <hi>Thou arte</hi> Peter, <hi>and vpon this</hi> Rocke <hi>I will builde my church,</hi> they with tooth and nayle labour to enforce, that Saint <hi>Peter</hi> is the Churches foundation, that vpon him (as on a Rocke) it is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded: as if theſe wordes, <hi>on this rocke</hi> were ſpoken of <hi>Peters</hi> perſon, and (which more is) of al Romiſh Pops ſucceeding in that Sea. Let vs exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the Text. Our Sauior deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Apoſtles, whome they did ſay him to be? <hi>Peter</hi> (in the name of all the reſt) anſwereth: <hi>Thou arte the Christ, the ſonne of the liuing God.</hi> Then Ieſus ſaide vnto him, <hi>Bleſſed arte thou Simon the ſonne of Ionas, for fleſh and bloud hath not reuealed it to thee, but my Father which is in heauen. And I ſay vnto thee, Thou arte Peter, and vppon this</hi> Rocke <hi>I will builde my Church.</hi> Vpon which Rocke? vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Peter?</hi> Then hee woulde haue ſaid, <hi>Thou arte Peter, and vpon thee:</hi>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:184222:41"/> not vpon this rocke) I will builde. The change of ſpeech, from <hi>The</hi> to <hi>This,</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> thou <hi>Peter,</hi> to <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> vppon <hi>This very Rocke,</hi> it argueth, that Ieſus would haue <hi>Peter</hi> to looke from himſelfe to ſome other perſon or thing. If to ſome other perſon, then only to him ſelfe, whom <hi>Peter</hi> had confeſſed to be the very Meſsiah. Which Chriſt is onely ſayd to be the Rocke, 1. <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin</hi> 10.4. The worde <hi>Foundation</hi> is communicated alſo with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles and Prophets, but the tearme Rocke is neuer giuen vnto anye meere creature: For hee that is God, can onely be the rocke of our ſaluation. And to keepe people from applying the tearme Rocke vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> the Holy-ghoſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after recordateth, how (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of his euill counſaile ſoone af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) our Sauiour ſaith vnto him<note place="margin">Matth. 16.23</note> 
               <hi>Get thee behind me Satan, thou arte an of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence vnto me, &amp;c.</hi> And not long af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:184222:41"/> hee three times forſweareth his Maiſter. Yea, after he hadde recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued (in the day of Pentecoſt) a ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Holy-ghoſt, he halteth in his miniſterie, and draweth <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> into the ſame diſſimulation (<hi>Galathians</hi> chap 2. verſe 11. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) for which the holy apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth him to the face, and blameth him. And that this was Saint <hi>Peter</hi> the Apoſtle (and not ſome other <hi>Cephas,</hi> as ſome malitious Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts haue lately vrged, but indeede an auntient errour) firſt obſerue how they oppoſe to <hi>Paul,</hi> who ſaith it was <hi>Peter</hi> (whome in the Syriacke terme hee before calleth<note n="*" place="margin">Elias in Thisbi affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that Simon (Ieſus of Nazareth his diſciple) he was called Cepha, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſignifieth Strength.</note> 
               <hi>Cephas</hi>) but alſo vnto the antient Fathers, as <hi>Tertullian, (in praeſcriptionibus aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus haeret.) Ambroſe (in ep. Gala cap.</hi> 2.) <hi>Chryſostome</hi> on the <hi>Galat.</hi> chap. 2.) <hi>Auguſtine contra mendac. ad Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentium cap.</hi> 12.) <hi>Ierome</hi> on <hi>Galat.</hi> 2. <hi>Cyrill (contra Iulian. li.</hi> 9. <hi>in fine.)</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Collecting it out of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines epiſtle to Ierome, as alſo out of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. So doth Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas on the ſame place.</note> 
               <hi>Bae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da</hi> on <hi>Galath.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea heerein
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:184222:42"/> they oppoſe vnto <hi>Gregorius Magnus</hi> their Pope, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>futing the ſame fond fancie in his eighteenth homily vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Ezekiel, post B.</hi> Thus the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts propound vnto vs weake foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dation, <hi>Peter</hi> for <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the Creator.</p>
            <p>To ſhutte vp this poynt briefly, hearken to <hi>Augustines</hi> teſtimonie: <q>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. in Ioh. ttact. 124.</note>The Church is founded vppon the Rocke whereon <hi>Peter</hi> tooke his name.<note n="*" place="margin">Non enim a Petro Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra, ſed Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trus a Petra, &amp;c.</note> For the Rocke was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued of <hi>Peter,</hi> but <hi>Peter</hi> of the <hi>Rocke:</hi> euen as Chriſt is not ſo termed, of Christian, but Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of Christ. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ppon this <hi>Rocke</hi> therefore <hi>(ſaieth hee)</hi> whome thou haſt confeſſed, I will build my Church: for the <hi>Rocke</hi> was <hi>CHRIST,</hi> vpon which foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation alſo <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe is buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. <hi>Whereunto ioyne that of</hi> I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidore:<note n="*" place="margin">Iſid. hiſp. lib. 7. etymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logiarum c. 9</note> 
                  <hi>Peter</hi> tooke his name of the <hi>Rocke,</hi> that is, of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> vppon whome the church is founded: For
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:184222:42"/> 
                  <hi>Chriſt</hi> was the <hi>Rocke,</hi> vpon which foundation, <hi>Peter</hi> himſelfe was alſo builded. <hi>If they will that</hi> Peter <hi>ſhoulde be, in ſome ſenſe, a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then they muſt admitte all the reſidue of the Apoſtles in the ſame reſpect to be foundations.</hi>
               </q> And that is it which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his <hi>Apocal.</hi> 22.14. ſpeaketh of, when hee ſeeth this <hi>Ieruſhalem</hi> to haue twelue foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dations, and in them, the names of the twelue Apoſtles.</p>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>Obiection.</head>
               <p>But <hi>Peter</hi> only had the keyes gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to him.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>Firſt, that is nothing to this: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, it is falſe: for the keys (name<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly, the power of binding and loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) is afterwardes giuen to many others, euen to the whole Church, ſo well as vnto him, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.22, 23. And this <hi>Origen</hi> preciſely (from the ſame place of <hi>Iohn</hi>) doth prooue in his Homily on <hi>Mathew</hi> 16. not to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:184222:43"/> ſpeake of other Ancients, (as <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an de ſimplicit. praelat. Aug. ſuper Ioh.</hi> 124. <hi>Tertull. ſcorp. aduerſ. Gnoſtio. c.</hi> 10. <hi>Rabanus c.</hi> 8. <hi>de poenit. Anſbert. li.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 5 <hi>in Apoc. &amp;c.</hi>) who grant, that in <hi>Peter</hi> was conſidered the church, to whom the power is giuen of bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and looſing ſpiritually.</p>
               <p>If we conſider Faith, that is, the Goſpel to bee the foundation of the Church, then that is it which diuers haue well vnderſtood: ſeeing Faith is the hand which coupleth Chriſt and his church together. Hence it is that <hi>Chryſ.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſ. ſerm. de Pente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſte, Super hanc petram, non dixit ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Petrum &amp;c.</note> thus writeth: Vpon this Rocke, not vpon <hi>Peter: for not vpon man, but vpon the Faith Chriſt buildes his church. And what was that Faith?</hi> (namely) <hi>Thou art Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing God. Nyſſenu (in testim. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect. ex vet. testa.)</hi> vtters the ſame. So do <hi>Theophil (in Mat.</hi> 16.) <hi>Smarag.</hi> on the ſame place: and <hi>Vict. Antiochenus</hi> ſaith, that fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this faith &amp; ſound do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, <hi>Peter</hi> receiued his name, on
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:184222:43"/> 
                  <hi>Mar.</hi> 3. not to mention any others. Thus, reſpect we ſcripture, or heare we the Antients their teſtimony, the Romaniſts ſtill are found looſers.</p>
               <p>For the Browniſts, what foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation doe they by their neceſſarie conſecution propound to vs? This forſooth, <hi>The outward Constitution of the Church,</hi> that is, <hi>The forme of plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and church-gouernement,</hi> and this is their <hi>Puppis</hi> and <hi>Prora,</hi> the load-ſtar of their Courſe. Inſomuch as they deny to haue communion in prayer, in preaching, in ſacrament with any ſuch Church whatſoeuer, which hath not bin ſo planted, &amp; is not ſo gouerned, as they conceiue of the Primitiue churches their planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and gouernement. And as they deny ſpirituall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion with <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> &amp; <hi>Scotland</hi> as failing in both: ſo let it be ſuch of the <hi>Dutch</hi> &amp; <hi>French</hi> churches as haue planted their chur. rightly in their own iudgement: yet bicauſe of ſom few things in gouern<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:184222:44"/> eccleſiaſticall, which they diſlike, they, not onely deny communion with them (yea for very hearing the worde) but alſo excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate ſuch of their people<note n="*" place="margin">So Maiſter Pe. Al. Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter M. Sl. &amp;c came to be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate.</note> as ſhall but ioyne with them in prayer or in preaching. Whereby it commeth to paſſe, that this people (main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining that that their father <hi>Browne</hi> dare not) they conceiue of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, for the onely true viſible church of God which can be throw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly communicated with.</p>
               <p>Briefly to returne anſwere: firſt, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> they take it for granted, that the faith of Chriſt was amongſt vs firſt plan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted, by force of the ſword (not by preaching of the worde) whereby came to paſſe, that all wicked were receiued, &amp;c. Let it be ſo. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. in ep. 48.</note> indeede was once of opinion, that no compulſion herin was to be vſed, but (by his felow miniſters) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put in mind, how his owne citie was wholy Donatiſts, til feare of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:184222:44"/> lawes brought them from that ſchiſme, to catholike vnity, the good man changeth his minde, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadging ſuch Scripture, <hi>Prouerb.</hi> 9 9. and 29.19. &amp;c. And I woulde gladly know of theſe men, to what end a Chriſtian hath the ſword put into his hand, if not (with <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah, Ioſiah, Hezekiah, Ioſaphat, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa, &amp;c.)</hi> to driue the ſubiectes vnto outward conformity of holineſſe &amp; righteouſneſſe? Take away this vſe of the ſworde, and then ſo wel with Anabaptiſtes remooue Magiſtrate and his ſword out of the church.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>Obiection.</head>
               <p>But it was prophecied, that the Church ſhould be a voluntary peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, Pſal. 110.3. and Chriſt gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and planted his Church by the word onely.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer.</head>
               <p>The Anabaptiſts do apply theſe thinges aſwell to their purpoſe, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding further, <hi>The Primitiue churches
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:184222:45"/> had no Kings in them &amp;c.</hi> therefore <hi>Kings</hi> (as Kings) not of a true eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church. And thus Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme leadeth to Anabaptiſme. But leaſt the crie of theſe Lapwings draw me from my purpoſe, I leaue the Browniſt to anſwere the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt; and this ſhall be my an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere to the ſcripture and our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiours practiſe. It is true, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple were and did voluntarilie giue vp their names to Chriſt vpon the Goſpels preaching. Chriſt herein would not vſe the ſword: not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it had been vnlawfull (for he in himſelfe vſed a whip in the Temple, and forcibly ouerthrew their chaunging tables) but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (for the firſt plantation of the Goſpell) he ſaw it not to be expedient. The weakeſt and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheſt meanes (in mans iudgement, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1, 27, 28, 29,) he now did vſe, that ſo no fleſh ſhould reioice in his preſence. As he vſed onely
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:184222:45"/> his woord, ſo he choſe vnlearned men for the publication thereof. And becauſe none ſhould ſay, that it was no maruell, though ſimple ſubiects became Chriſtians, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſome of their Kings were firſt Chriſtians, the Apoſtle therefore before ſaid, <hi>Not many Mighty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not many Noble are called.</hi> To conclude now, <hi>That the Sword hath not his vſe in churches plantation &amp;c.</hi> they may aſwell conclude, <hi>That Noble men, wiſe and learned men, they haue nothing to doe in Church plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.</hi> Indeed, when there com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth a <hi>New-Christ,</hi> and <hi>new Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,</hi> we will either graunt they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude well: or elſe we wil hold them and the new Chriſt accurſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Secondly, they aſſume <hi>[That the ſword planted firſt the Faith here]</hi> which we deny. Firſt, it cannot be but the firſt plantation of the <hi>Faith</hi> whereſoeuer, it muſt bee by the <hi>Gospell</hi> preached. The ſword may
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:184222:46"/> make a noyſe together with the Words voice, but none can by the ſword alone take any knowledge of the Goſpell. Beſides, it appeareth by auncient record, that the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell came into this land in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles times, according to that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.18. <hi>Tertullian</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tertull. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſ. Iud. ca. 7.</note> ſaith, <hi>Britanno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum inacceſſa Romanis loca, Chriſto vero ſubdita &amp;c.</hi> That the Britans (euen in ſuch places as Romaines had not acceſſe vnto) they were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued to Chriſt. That <hi>S. Paul</hi> (after his firſt captiuitie at Rome) ſhould come into theſe partes, <hi>Theodoret</hi> writeth,<note place="margin">Theod. l. 9. de cur. Graec. affect. Niceph. l. 2. ca. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Nicephorus</hi> affirmeth that <hi>Simon Zelotes</hi> came into Britaine. And <hi>Iohn Bale</hi> (from auncient <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> our writer, and from others) af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth, that <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arimathia</hi> was ſent into Britain by <hi>Philip</hi> the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, after the diſperſion from the Galles, &amp; this to be about the yeere of our Lord 63. Yea, that <hi>Iames</hi> with ſome others did repaire to, and
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:184222:46"/> preach in <hi>Ireland, Vincentius</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Vinc. 8. c. 7.</note> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth. But more of this I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in my <hi>Antidoton.</hi> Who came firſt hither with the Goſpell, it skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not: ſure we are it came here, for we find it here, and the Brow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts againſt his owne ſoule muſt confeſſe it: except they will tell vs that them ſelues haue receaued the Goſpell vpon Sea, or in ſome fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne country. <hi>Obiection:</hi> But this proueth no way an orderly planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church to haue bin here. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Yes forſooth, except you wil haue a companie of beleeuers dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling together in the Faith (as the Church firſt did lodge in a myles compaſſe by <hi>Welles,</hi> now tearmed <hi>Glaſcon-bury</hi>) to liue without rule, without forme of true gouernment. If they liued at firſt like Libertines (which no ſober ſpirit can think) then we muſt greatly lament that none of the Browniſts were then with them for inſtructing them in
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:184222:47"/> diſcipline. <hi>Obiection:</hi> Let it be what ſoeuer it was, yet we find not true diſcipline now. <hi>Anſ.</hi> Some of you haue alſo ſaid, that neither we haue the Goſpell: but if ſome of you vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on better aduiſe do graunt we haue the Goſpell for the ſubſtance, I think ye had beſt graunt alſo diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline for the ſubſtance: that is, ſuch externall gouernment as (for the ſubſtance at leaſt) doth ſtand for the Goſpell, for Chriſt. And that the Goſpell ſhall ſo ſoundly be prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched, and gouernment ſo faithfully executed of any Churches in theſe laſt times, as was at firſt, none of wit can beleeue, becauſe our Sauior and the Apoſtles do fore-tell the contrarie (<hi>Math.</hi> 24, 37, 38, 39, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17, 22, 23. <hi>Math.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">My Antido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton openeth that point at large.</note> 13, 24, &amp;c. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4, 1, &amp;c. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3, 1, &amp;c. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uel.</hi> 13, 11, &amp;c. 2. <hi>Theſſ</hi> 2, 3, &amp;c.) and yet no reaſon nor warrant of run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning out of the Catholike wheat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field or Church, vnder a pretext of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:184222:47"/> Replantation: but rather to keepe within, and as we can, and may, to labour for Reformation.</p>
               <p>But where they ſay, <hi>You want Chriſts gouernment, and in the roume thereof you haue Antichristes, and therfore we ſeperate,</hi> I more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly anſwer. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, (after <hi>Peters</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion in <hi>Math.</hi> 16) our Sauior doth not promiſe that outward Church-gouernment ſhall preuaile for euer againſt <hi>Hell-gates</hi> (and themſelues graunt it hath not) but only <hi>A true being of the Church,</hi> by reaſon of the Rock wheron it ſhould be builded. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, let them marke that <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> maketh no confeſſion of Church diſcipline (for as yet he had not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that) but of Chriſt Ieſus to be as verilie the Son of God (vnſeen of fleſh and blood) as he was man, well ſeen of fleſh &amp; blood. Who beeing the Chriſt or Meſſiah, did verily car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with it that there was no other by whom Saluation was wholie or in
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:184222:48"/> part to be effected. And the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, beliefe, and apprehenſion of this (not exteriour diſcipline) is the eſſential foundation of the Church: Which who ſo holdeth in the vnitie of the Catholike Church, they are to be held of this Catholike Citie, and not becauſe of imperfections to be ſeuered from: becauſe <hi>Iehouah</hi> is <hi>Shammah, There.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, let them conſider, that as outward Church gouernment is not the mark or badge euer of true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans (for in the Browniſts iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, many of the Anabaptiſts haue that: and we know that <hi>Ieſabel</hi> with her ſpiritual children, <hi>Balaams</hi> ſectaries, the faction of beaſtly <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colaitans</hi> &amp;c. (<hi>Reuel.</hi> 2. &amp; 3.) they were in the Aſian Churches, right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſtabliſhed and poſſeſſed of right gouernment, (but yet bearing the badge of Antichriſt) ſo neither is humane regiment a marke euer of falſe Chriſtians. For if Chriſt his
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:184222:48"/> gouernment externall, it can not cauſe all vnder it to be (vnto vs) true viſible Chriſtians: much leſſe can humane regiment, or Antichriſts outward gouernment, cauſe all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it to be (of vs) reputed An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtes. Seeing Anti-chriſtes gouernment can not haue more vice in it, then there is vertue in Chriſtes. Fourthly, they know not what Antichriſts marke is: for if euery good thing be not the marke of a true Chriſtian (for <hi>Arrius, Neſtorius,</hi> yea, euery Heretike hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſome good thinges) ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can euery bad thing be the badge of Antichriſt: for then eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man ſhould be Antichriſtian, ſeing euery man (at leaſt ſomtimes) hath ſome bad thing viſible in him. As Antichriſt is oppoſed to Chriſt, ſo in nothing ſo much, as in the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rie foundation of <hi>Religion;</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r which the Apoſtle <hi>S. Paul</hi> tear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth him <hi>Anti-keimenos,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.4.</note> the <hi>Layer
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:184222:49"/> of an oppoſite foundation.</hi> And in very troth, as it is the verie eſſentiall truth of the Goſpell, which is the mark of a true Chriſtian: ſo, it is the very fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall falſhood of Antichriſt, for the which he is entitled Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, &amp; his members Antichriſts. The foundation falſe (not hay, ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, &amp;c. vpon a true foundation, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. &amp;c.) is the beaſtes marke differencing his people eſſentially from Chriſtes. <hi>Obiect.</hi> But the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaying, <hi>Let euery man take heed</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>how</hi> he builds, not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, what he builds; it argueth he there ſpeaketh of the manner of teaching, not of the matter taught. <hi>I anſwer:</hi> He inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth both maner and matter. And that may be ſeen; Firſt, by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the 2. chap. &amp; the 1. verſe with that which foloweth there, &amp; in this chapter: for he compareth not only his plaine manner of teaching with humane Eloquence, but alſo, the plaine matter of the Goſpell with
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:184222:49"/> the worlds wiſdom, which elſwhere he tearmeth<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 2.8.</note> 
                  <hi>Philoſophie.</hi> Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, gold, ſiluer, &amp;c. hay, ſtubble, &amp;c. they cannot in any proprietie ſo much reſemble manner, as matter: ſpecially compared with Fire which is not appointed ſo much to trie the manner, as the matter or thing it ſelf. Thirdly, ſeeing Eloquence may ſtand with Chriſt the foundation: firſt, for that it is the gift of God: 2. is ſanctified to his people, <hi>Exod.</hi> 4.10.11, <hi>Eccles.</hi> 12.9.10, <hi>Act.</hi> 18.24, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.5. Laſtly, an hundred ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers may be called together for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining fully what is the Primitiue forme of Church-regiment, and 3. of them (though otherwiſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men) not be found in one iudgment for all things. How vnwiſe therfore are theſe people, that about the forme of diſcipline, do rend them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the Catholike Citie of god! Our Sauiour foretold that ther ſhould be ſuch ſchiſmatical ſpirites,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:184222:50"/> who in theſe confuſed times would crie, Come into the deſert, come into the ſecret places, Chriſt is here: but therewith he ſaith to his ſheepe, <hi>Go not thither, nor follow them, Luk.</hi> 17.23. Thus much briefly touching the foundation of this new Citie <hi>Ieho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uah-Shammah.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="89" facs="tcp:184222:50"/>
            <head>This that followeth was not vttered, as being preuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>by the time.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, it now remayneth I ſpeak of the Citizens, &amp; that ſo brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie as I can.</p>
            <p>The Citizens are as the Citie is conſidered. This Citie being the Church extended from the Eaſt to the Weſt, it muſt be conſidered, either as exiſting of all Chriſtians good and bad (and ſo Heretikes, Sciſmatikes, Phariſaicall profeſſors &amp;c. are all Citizens, though bad Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens:)
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:184222:51"/> Or elſe, as it exiſteth only of ſuch as are ſanctified (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the end of their Election, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4.) who are verie deed the liuely members of Chriſt Ieſus. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the firſt conſideration all are Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, by reaſon they haue recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the outward badge or cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaunce of Chriſt, and ſo by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme haue giuen vp their names to Chriſt. Who before they appeare euill, are of vs to be deemed true Chriſtians: but appearing euill, and not obaying the Churches voice for repentance, they are to be denied all familiar communion (ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in eccleſiaſticall ordinances) but not without ſome hope that God wil in time, recouer them: ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the firſt excommunication is but for humbling the proud fleſh, that ſo the ſpirit may, in the Lord his good day be ſaued, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4.5. As for the ſecond excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (tearmed <hi>Maran-atha,</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <pb n="91" facs="tcp:184222:51"/> 16.22,) it is ſeldom inflicted on any by the Church, becauſe ſuch is their Apoſtacie from Chriſt, as for the which the Church denieth after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to ſacrifice or pray for them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, compared with <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26, &amp; 1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.6, and eaſily the Church dare not ſo iudge and leaue any ſoule vnto the <hi>Lord his comming</hi> to iudgement, as the <hi>Syri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ake</hi> phraſe <hi>(Maran-atha)</hi> importeth.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Máréa</hi> Dominus, Dan. 2.47. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Atha,</hi> Venit, vt in Ezra. 5.3.</note> And that the Church is conſidered in ſuch ſence (namely to conſiſt of good and bad) it is to be heeded firſt in her types (as in <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, and <hi>Iſraels</hi> congregation, as alſo in ſuch of the New teſtaments ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Math.</hi> 3.12, and 13.24. &amp;c. and there in <hi>verſ.</hi> 47. &amp;c. and 24.40, 41. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.20, with many of like nature. And ſo are ordinarilie vnderſtood of our Auncients.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> That the church is alſo vnderſtood of ſuch as be really ſanctified and borne anew through the immortall
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:184222:52"/> ſeede of God his word, and the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward operation of his ſpirit, it may appeare: firſt from the end of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and vocation, which is, vnto ſanctification of the Spirit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vppon they are called <hi>Saints,</hi> or <hi>Holy-ones, Rom.</hi> 1.7, and 16.2.15, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2, &amp; 6.1, &amp; 16.1.15. <hi>&amp; alibi ſaepe,</hi> compared with, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.4. <hi>Iohn</hi> 15.3, &amp; 17.17: Secondly, by ſuch expreſſe teſtimonie, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.25, 26, 27, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.14, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.9. And of this ſort of Citizens is that <hi>Ieruſhalem</hi> from heauen, and that Tabernacle of God with men, which <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſeeth in <hi>Reuel.</hi> 21.2.3. vnderſtood ſo<note place="margin">Rabanus ca. 8. de modo poenitentiae. Bale hereon. Beza in ſer. 20. of Chr. paſsion. Tho. Aquin. on Galat. 4.26.</note> of Auncient and moderne writers: though ſomtime of the triumphant Church alſo.</p>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>Obiection.</head>
               <p>Here is a citty wherein no vnclean thing enters, but the beſt of God his people here haue vncleane things in them: therefore here they cannot be
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:184222:52"/> the Citizens of this new <hi>Ieruſhalem.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>Anſwer,</head>
               <p>The Antecedent is true, but the illation (or conſequent) is falſe. For they are ſayd to be <hi>Cleane,</hi> not ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, but reſpectiuely: that is, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect that they are alredy in the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi> of regeneration cleanſed ſo in part, as in Chriſt their head it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered Abſolute and perfect. And that in S. <hi>Iohn</hi> cittizeas there be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfections, it may appeare in 22. chap. verſe 2. where hee ſayth, that the leaues of this citties wood (the <hi>Tree of life,</hi> Chriſt Ieſus in his word and ſpirit) they <hi>were to heale the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with.</hi> Whereas the healing of vs (in regarde of our ſpirituall ſores) it appertaineth in proprietie to this life, beſides that the Lord tearmeth things that are not, as if they were: becauſe his <hi>Velle</hi> is <hi>Eſſe,</hi> his preſent <hi>Wil,</hi> is preſent <hi>Worke:</hi> but vnto vs reuealed in time. This holy people (for if the firſt fruites be holy, ſo is
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:184222:53"/> the whole lump; and if the roote be holy, ſo are the branches, <hi>Ro.</hi> 11.16) for theyr ſakes the wicked tares are ſpared, <hi>Math.</hi> 13.29. yea the Sodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miticall worlde (were it not for this righteous <hi>Lot</hi>) ſhould ſoon be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with fire &amp; brimſton. Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked within, wicked without, they al fare the better for this little Citties ſake: and yet they can intreate it no better, than <hi>Laban</hi> intreated <hi>Iaakob, Sodom</hi> intreated <hi>Lot</hi> &amp; his good an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, no better than <hi>Saul</hi> vnto <hi>Dauid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>While <hi>Iudahs Ieruſhalem</hi> ſtoode with her Temple and ceremonies, then theſe Citizens (for one gentle ſwallow makes not a ſummer) were the ſeede of <hi>Iaakob</hi> or <hi>Iſrael,</hi> pent vp within the typicall <hi>Canaan:</hi> but now this new citties people are ſtretched from Sea to Sea, from one ende of the world to an other; conſiſting of all nations and kinreds, and people, and tongues, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 7.9. Sayd I of all tongues? Yea: not onely all ſorts
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:184222:53"/> of people, but all ſortes of tongues are to ſtand before the Throne of Chriſt, and prayſe him. Not onely the Hebrew, the Greeke, and Latin tongues (wherein our Sauiours <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> was written) but all the tongues that were giuen vnto the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles in <hi>Actes</hi> 2. ch. whereby they were enabled to preach the doctrine of faith vnto all ſortes of people. Which were a ſufficient confutati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Romaniſts ſeruice in ſole Latine (compared with 1. <hi>Corin.</hi> 14.16.) But becauſe no inſtrument ſhal be lacking, for cutting off that euill, themſelues now at laſt haue turned the new teſtament into Engliſh, for euery Lay man to looke into: as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo haue made Engliſh Manuels of prayer, beſides their turning of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus his Pſalter</hi> (blaſphemouſly ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led) into our language: <hi>So great is the Truth, and preuaileth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, theſe are that <hi>Ieruſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> which is here tearmed <hi>Iehouah
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:184222:54"/> Shammah. The Lord is there:</hi> Where? in this Citty, in this people, for they are the <hi>Habitation</hi> and <hi>Temple</hi> of the mighty God of <hi>Iaakob.</hi> God riſeth vp in them, and they grow vp in God: and ſo (oh depth of wiſdom &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie) God and Man becommeth <hi>One.</hi> The diuell at firſt ſaide to <hi>Euah,</hi> that in eating the forbidden fruit, they ſhould become AS GODS. He meant <hi>As Diuels, Blacke gods:</hi> and yet hee ſpake truer than hee was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware. For as the creature cannot be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the Creator, ſo we are not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come really <hi>Gods,</hi> but we (through his free fauour that called Light out of Darkneſſe) are become really <hi>As Gods:</hi> not <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Elohim,</hi> but<note place="margin">Gen. 3 5.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Kelohim.</hi> Vnto this City and people appertaine the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uileges of grace in this life, &amp; the ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hibition of glory in the other life. In a word, al the things of God, are for theſe people, called to be <hi>As gods:</hi> for in his preſence is the fulneſſe of ioy,
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:184222:54"/> and at his right hand are pleaſures for euermore, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.11.</p>
               <p>Much contention (about our Lordes yeere 666) was betweene <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Constantinople</hi> for ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie vniuerſall. <hi>Rome</hi> woulde bee chiefe, becauſe it had beene the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient ſeate of the Emperours. <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinoples,</hi> Biſhop woulde haue it, becauſe <hi>Constantine</hi> (the firſt chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Emperour) hadde of <hi>Bizantium</hi> made it <hi>Constantino-polis,</hi> and ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſted it with his owne name, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it alſo an emperors ſeate. Marke, that neither of them could alleadge then any <hi>Donation</hi> from <hi>Constantine.</hi> If there had beene then ſuch a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation as now they tell vs of, howe greatly would it haue helped <hi>Romes</hi> plea? But as neuer of theſe Aunti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents it is once mentioned, viz. <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius, Entropius, Ruffinus, Socrates, Theodoret, Euagrius, Paulus Diaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Beda, Oroſius, Zonaras, Nicepho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus:</hi> Nor of <hi>Ierome, Damaſus, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thanaſius,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:184222:55"/> Baſil, Ambroſe, Optatus Mileuitanus, Gregorius Niſſenus, Gregorius Nazianzenus, Auguſtine, Chryſostome:</hi> nor of the Romaine Biſhoppes in the Councells, which then had beene of much moment) ſo,<note n="*" place="margin">See Auen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus lib 2 de rebus Boio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
                  <hi>Pius ſecundus</hi> Pope (a man ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry expert in Antiquities) he laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed this toy to ſcorne, accounting it <hi>fabulam inanem,</hi> a vayne fable.<note n="*" place="margin">Naucl. in generat. 11 ſuae crono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph.</note> 
                  <hi>Nau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clerus</hi> fathers it on <hi>Iſidore,</hi> but in his antient Books no ſuch thing found. And no ſooner ſtart vp this <hi>Fict-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation</hi> but the lerned oppoſed. This did <hi>Marſilius Patauinus</hi> in his <hi>Defen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of Peace.</hi> So dooth <hi>Laurentius Valla</hi> in his Declamation. So didde <hi>Antoninus Archiepiſcopus Florenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Part. tit.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 2. §. 8.</note> in his hiſtorie. So doth cardinall <hi>Cuſanus</hi> in his Catholike Concor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 2. ſent vnto <hi>Baſils</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell. So doth <hi>Aeneas Siluius</hi> (after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Pope) in his dialog. So doth <hi>Raphael Volateran</hi> in the <hi>life of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine: Hierony. Paulus Cattalanus</hi>
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:184222:55"/> doctor of both laws, and chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine to Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, in his booke entituled, <hi>Practica cancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lariae Apostolicae.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltrich Hutten</hi> writing to Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the tenth, vppon <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alla</hi> his booke, hee ſaieth plainly, that the Donation was forged <hi>per pſeudo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pontifices Orientis,</hi> by the Eaſterne falſe-popes: not to ſpeake of <hi>Luther</hi> and others. But to finiſh that point; what time <hi>Bizantiums</hi> Biſhop be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne to labour for ſuch vniuerſall headſhip, <hi>Gregorius Magnus</hi> biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> he that in humiliation firſt tooke the title <hi>Seruus ſeruorum,</hi> he is bolde hereupon to<note n="*" place="margin">Li. 4 c. 34.</note> write thus: <hi>Ego fidenter dico, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q>I conſtantly affirm, whoſoeuer calles himſelfe vniuerſall prieſt (or deſires ſo to be called) in that his puft vp eſtate, hee fore-run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth Antichriſt: and in his 39. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle hee tearmeth it <hi>Nomen blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemiae</hi>) a title of blaſphemie, which title ſoone after <hi>Gregories</hi> time was by
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:184222:56"/> bloudy <hi>Phocas</hi> giuen to the Pope of the ſeauen hilled citty.</q> And thus, where on <hi>Rome</hi> before was written <hi>Roma aeterna,</hi> cenſured by<note place="margin">Hieron. in epiſt. ad Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaſiam.</note> 
                  <hi>Ierome</hi> for a name of blaſphemy: nowe by their owne Popes cenſure, that Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>Arch-prieſt</hi> hath to himſelfe aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed no better. Thus their clay &amp; yron will not be ioyned together: no baulme will cure this <hi>Babel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But wil the faythfull know what Citty is Eterne? That is this new Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, the City of the Saints. Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh power may oppreſſe it, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſuppreſſe it. Wilt thou knowe what City is ſupreame? That is this <hi>Ieruſhalem</hi> from Heauen heauenly. Wilt thou know to what Biſhop al ſupremacie vniuerſall is due? That is, to Chriſt Ieſus, who himſelfe is <hi>Iehouah,</hi> and hath obtayned a name aboue all Names, and he is the head of the Churches bodie, [<hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 1.18.] he is the beginning and firſt borne of the dead, that in ALL
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:184222:56"/> THINGS he might haue the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence. And this vniuerſall ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie was figured darkly vnder the <hi>Hie-prieſt</hi> of <hi>Ieruſhalems</hi> Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who had ſuch dignitie ouer that ſhadowing Church, as none but he might enter the moſt holy place: only to him in the laſt place were difficult matters brought for deciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and by his death were ſuch ſet free, as before for vnawares blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed had taken ſanctuarie. All which beeing ſhadowes of good things to come, the bodie whereof was Chriſt [<hi>Heb.</hi> 10.1, and 9.11.12, <hi>Coloſſ.</hi> 2.17.] now we are to conſider al anew, as beſeemeth that which is ſubſtantiall, not ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall.</p>
               <p>Thus the Citie and the Citizens are the ſame: and <hi>Iehouah</hi> is <hi>There</hi> one with the ſame, though not the ſame. In this Citie he dwels gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Citizens, ſubduing all their ſenſes, all their affections, the whole
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:184222:57"/> man to himſelfe. And round about this Citie he cauſeth his Angels to pitch their tentes of defence. Nay, which more is,<note place="margin">Pſ. 125.2. Zech. 2.5.</note> as the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines were round about the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picall Ieruſhalem, ſo is <hi>Iehouah</hi> himſelfe (as a conſuming fire) round about his people henceforth and for euer. To the Citizens a comfort, but to their aduerſaries a terrour.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> For the Aduerſaries they muſt know, that they band not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues only againſt Man, but againſt armies of Angels, yea, againſt the God of hoſtes himſelfe: for <hi>Iehouah is There.</hi> He that toucheth theſe Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, he toucheth the apple of his eye, he daſheth himſelfe againſt a wall of conſuming fire.<note place="margin">Reuel. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 7, 8.9.</note> Againſt this Citie doth <hi>Gog</hi> (the cloked ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſarie) and <hi>Magog</hi> (the <hi>Open ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi>) together with their innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble army convene in One: but af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they haue compaſſed the tents
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:184222:57"/> of the Saints and the beloued Citie round about, behold fire ſhall come downe from heauen and deuoure them. It is no bourding with Saints. Againſt God his Citie in her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties dominions, how haue coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and vn-couered enemies riſen vp (at home &amp; abroad, by land and by Sea) but what was their end? The Egyptian Pharaoh of <hi>Spaine,</hi> his Chariot-armadoes ſlunke into the Seas channels, the windes of God fought againſt them, and da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed their huge rigged fleete aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.<note place="margin">I allude to Iudg. 5.28. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>Rome</hi> (the mother of <hi>Spaines Siſera.</hi>) ſhe looked out at a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow and cried thorough the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, why is the Chariot ſo long a comming? why tarrie the wheeles of his chariots? Romes wiſe Ladies anſwered her: yea, ſhe anſwered her ſelfe with her owne wordes, thus: haue they not gotten and they deuide the ſpoil, the Crowne, Earle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, and Church reuenewes
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:184222:58"/> of England? Euery man hath a mayde or two. <hi>Siſera</hi> hath a pray of diuers colours, a pray of ſundry co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors made of needle worke: of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers colors of needle work on both ſides, for the chiefe of the ſpoile.</q> But ſorrie fooles, through God his goodnes, a woman (a <hi>Virgin</hi> Queene) ſhe triumphed ouer <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera.</hi> For domeſtick aduerſaries, who haue banded together<note place="margin">I allude to 1. King. 1.</note> for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointing <hi>Adonijah,</hi> but poore ſoules they haue conſumed themſelues as wax before the Sunne.<note place="margin">Deborahs prayer in Iudg. 5.31.</note> So let all thine enemies periſh ô Lord: but they that loue him ſhall be as the Sun when he riſeth in his fortitude.</p>
               <p>But here ſome will obiect: Either <hi>Iehouah</hi> dwelleth not in and about his Church, or els he hath promiſed no ſuch protection, for we ſee many of his people to fall by the ſword &amp;c. I anſwer, there is no contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction in all this: for as he dwelleth in, and round about them for pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:184222:58"/> ſo he denieth them not the thing he promiſeth, but performes it with aduantage. He lets Abels blood to be ſpilt, he ſuffers Stephen to be ſtoned &amp;c. but what then? Hath he not protected them to the death? It is appointed that all men ſhall die (for death is gone ouer all) and then commeth iudgement. Abell did but die, Stephen did but die, and all muſt die. But marke, thoſe that die in the Lord are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, for they thenceforth reſt from their labours, <hi>Reuel.</hi> 14.13. This life is but a vallie of teares, a priſon, a purgatorie: when his people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moue hence, teares are taken away, no more priſoners, free from neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of purgation, no more labours, for they reſt in the Lord: yea, they enter into Abrahams boſome of bliſſe, as did Lazarus: they are with Chriſt Ieſus in the kingdome of glory, euen the very howre of<note n="“" place="margin">Conſider that in Iohn 19.31.32. and it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be eaſily iudged but at the very vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhot of the day he dyed, and that day he was to be with Chriſt. Luk. 23.43.</note> their death, as was promiſed to the peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:184222:59"/> thiefe on the Croſſe:<note place="margin">At the elea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenth houre he entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yarde, the Church: and in thend of the twelfth houre (for the day hath but twelue houres) he receiued the penny. Matth. 20.9</note> and as ſaint <hi>Paule</hi> beleeued when hee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, that it was beſt for him to die, that ſo hee might goe to the Lorde: and no maruell, for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious (ſaieth the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>) in the eies of the Lorde, is the death of his Saints. If it bee good for them to ſtay heere, they ſhall with <hi>Iudahs</hi> three yong gentlemen be vnſinged in the fornace, vnharmed with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> of the greedy Lions, for the Lorde knoweth howe to deliuer His in the day of trouble. If it bee not good in ſome reſpect for them here to ſtay, then he remoues them from an inconſtant eſtate to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, from ſadnes to gladnes, from a temporary life, to an eternall: in a word, from hell, to heauen. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They looſe a ruſty counter, and therewith obtaine eternall treaſure. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, protection is for good, not for euill, therefore no longer hee protecteth them heere, becauſe
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:184222:59"/> longer it ſhoulde not bee good for them to be here.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Agayne, their body onely loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſuch protection, not theyr ſoule; for the bleſſed Angelles at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the pooreſt <hi>Lazarus</hi> for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veying the ſoule into eternall bliſſe.</p>
               <p>Beſides, neyther is the body (in trueth, howſoeuer in ſhewe) vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>protected in death and graue: for as not an haire ſhall fall, but by the heauenly Fathers appoynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo neyther is the body vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarded of his good Spirite, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the fleſh doth reſt in hope.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, although theyr bodies fall by ſundry deaths (and all but death) yet euer are they victors: Firſt, in that their ſoules (the chiefer part) they triumph, nor can of man be ſlain: Secondly, in that the whole body of this Citty, neuer can of man be put to death, but as the pruining of a vine, cauſeth it rather to encreaſe in good, ſo is all cutting afflictions
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:184222:60"/> ſanctified to the Churches encreaſe: <hi>Sanguis Martyrum, ſemen Eccleſiae.</hi> And warriours neuer ſay they are conquered, (notwithſtanding the loſſe of many men) when ſo the day is theirs in the end of the day. And euer in the end, the Church is found the conquerour: her enemies dying for euer, but her members raized vp to glorie, as not euer ſlaine, but hauing been in a ſleep or ſlumber.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iehouah-Shammah,</hi> the Lorde is with his Church; and if the Lord be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> with vs, then <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, who can be againſt vs? Nor diuell, nor man, much leſſe inferiour crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Though<note place="margin">Rom. 8.36.37. &amp;c.</note> we be killed all the day long, accounted as ſheepe for the ſlaughter: neuertheleſſe in all theſe things we are more than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querours, through him that loued vs. For I am perſwaded (ſayeth S. <hi>Paul</hi> to the Romanes) that neyther death, nor life, nor angells, nor prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, nor powers, nor thinges
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:184222:60"/> preſent, nor thinges to come: nor height, nor depth, nor any other cre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ature ſhalbe able to ſeperat vs from the loue of God, which is in Chriſt Ieſus our Lord.</p>
               <p>What ſhall we returne vnto the Lord, who of [<note n="*" place="margin">So is the Hebrew.</note>
                  <hi>lo gnammi] Not-my-people,</hi> hath made and pronounced vs <hi>[gnammi] my people:</hi> that where before we were many Nations now he hath made vs One people, one nation.<note place="margin">Beda in 1. Cor. 12. ex Aug. pſ. 85.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na gens, vna patria, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <q>Wee now are (ſayeth a holy Father of this Citty) <hi>One Nation, One Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</hi> Our countrey is heauenly, our countrey is <hi>Ieruſhalem.</hi> Whoſoeuer is not thereof a Cittizen, he pertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to this people. But whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer is thereof a Cittizen, he is of this people of God. And this people is ſtretched forth from the Eaſt to the Weſt, from the North, and the ſea, it is ſtretcht through the foure parts of the whole world. For all his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding fauours irradiating this Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:184222:61"/> this Church, this People, it reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that we all walke more worthie our holy calling: more worthy ſuch a Gouernour as is <hi>Iehouah.</hi>
                  </q> Shall I with the Pſalmiſt ſay vnto all our ſoules, * <hi>Lift vp your heades ye gates, and lift ye vppe yee euerlasting doores, &amp; the King of Glory ſhall come in?</hi> Yea I ſay ſo: and I moreouer ſay, Take heede you fetch not in the Lorde of life, with ſpreading braunches, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and crying to day <hi>Hoſanna,</hi> &amp; then to morrow betray him, &amp; cry, <hi>Cruci-fige.</hi> It beſeemeth Princes to cut traitors from their Citty, and it ſhall neuer vnbeſeeme God to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute ſpeedy vengeance on the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. This Citties gates Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> ſeeth euer open to the Elect (ſuch as cleanſe themſelues by vnfained re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentaunce) come they from what coaſt ſoeuer. Vpon euery coaſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen three gates, and euery gate an entire pearle: by ſacred Trinitie in vnitie, euen by their ſweete loue, of
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:184222:61"/> more worth than any pearle, al muſt enter. For Porters there ſtand An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gells (euen the twelue great Angels of the particular Churches) who by God his word inuite the repentant. If <hi>Dauid</hi> accounted it ſuch an hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe to ſtand on this Cities thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſholde, what glory muſt it bee, to walke in the ſtreetes of pure golde, to haue the face of <hi>Iehouah</hi> for theyr <hi>Sunne-ſhine,</hi> to haue the Lord God almighty, and the Lambe for their Temple, and to haue for fellow Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizens, <hi>Adam, Habel, Sheth, Henoch, Noah, Shem, Heber, Abraham, Iſaac, Iaakob, Ioſeph, Moſes, Aaron, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhuah, Samſon, Samuel, Dauid, Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Hezekiah, Ioſiah, Daniel, Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubbabel, Ezra, Nehemiah,</hi> in a word, all the Patriarchs, Prophets, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, true Martyres and Confeſſors of all ages? As all waters returne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Sea, ſo all happineſſes returne into this Citties vnitie, gathered by the Holy-ghoſt, founded on Ieſus
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:184222:62"/> Chriſt, gouerned by God almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
               <p>But without this Cities vnitie,<note n="*" place="margin">Reuel. 21.8.</note> are dogs and inchaunters and whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, and murtherers and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, and whoſoeuer loueth or maketh lyes. The holy enlightned as Iſrael in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> but the vn-holie darkned as the Aegyptians in the land of <hi>Mizraim.</hi> God within, the Deuill without: for as there is no third gouernour, ſo there is no third Place. Theſe that are not of <hi>Micha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els</hi> ſide, all theſe are of the Dragons ſide: who ſhall fight, but not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile, neither ſhall they haue any place in heauen.</p>
               <p>As the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> with reuerent admiration ſhutteth vp his Prophecie with this, <hi>The name of that Citie</hi> (that is, of the New-teſtaments Church) <hi>from a Day,</hi> (euen from the time of typicall Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſhalems ende) <hi>ſhalbe Iehouah-Shamma, The Eternall is there:</hi> ſo I
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:184222:62"/> with <hi>S. Iohns</hi> ſpeach will finiſh my Sermon:<note place="margin">Reuel. 22.14</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed be they that doe his commaundements, that their right may be in the Tree of lyfe, and may enter in through the Gates</hi> [<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>] <hi>into That Citie.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:184222:63"/>
            <head>Errata in this Booke correct thus.</head>
            <p>Page 16. line 8. for <hi>that</hi> reade <hi>this</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Page 40 line 19. reade <hi>departed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pag. 45. li. 22. for <hi>Chron.</hi> reade <hi>chap.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:184222:63"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
